<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery, and confutation of the opinions, and practises of some false brethren, betwixt Bridge, and Lincolne: shewing how they agree in their opinions, with Pelagians; Papists; Arminians; in their practises, with Anabaptists. Wherein univerall redemption is confuted; and Gods absolute decree confirmed. / By John Wetherall, minister of Spridlington, near Lincolne. March 22. 1651. Imprimatur. John Downame.</title>
            <author>Wetherall, John, minister of Spridlington.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E661_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118118</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 101:E661[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery, and confutation of the opinions, and practises of some false brethren, betwixt Bridge, and Lincolne: shewing how they agree in their opinions, with Pelagians; Papists; Arminians; in their practises, with Anabaptists. Wherein univerall redemption is confuted; and Gods absolute decree confirmed. / By John Wetherall, minister of Spridlington, near Lincolne. March 22. 1651. Imprimatur. John Downame.</title>
                  <author>Wetherall, John, minister of Spridlington.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for William Wells, at the Princes Armes in Little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian sects --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118118:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A</hi> Diſcovery, <hi>and</hi> Confutation <hi>OF THE OPINIONS, AND PRACTISES Of ſome</hi> falſe Brethren, <hi>betwixt</hi> Bridge, <hi>and</hi> Lincolne: <hi>Shewing how they agree in their</hi> Opinions, <hi>with</hi> Pelagians; Papiſts; Arminians; <hi>in their</hi> Practiſes, <hi>with</hi> Anabaptiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> Univerſall Redemption <hi>is confuted; and</hi> Gods Abſolute Decree <hi>confirmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſo doe theſe alſo reſiſt the Truth: Men of corrupt Minds; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning the Faith: But they ſhall proceed no further; for their Folly ſhall be manifeſt unto all men; as theirs alſo was. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOHN WETHERALL, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Spridlington, <hi>near</hi> Lincolne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 22. 1651. Imprimatur. <hi>John Downame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Thomas Harper, <hi>for</hi> William Wells, <hi>at the Princes Armes in</hi> Little Brittain. 1652.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118118:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118118:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Did not thinke to have come forth in publick; My hearts deſire was, to hide my ſelfe in our little Hamlet: But God hath reſerved us to live; till all the Errours, that other Ages did but imagine, are Preached; yea and Printed in ours. Sectaries are waxen inſolent, like unto Serpents in Summer, that take courage to ſtep forth, and bite even the heels of Horſes, that their Riders may fall; They ſpare not, both in word and writing, to reproach our Religion, as a thing not countenanced by Antiquity; and our Miniſtery, as altogether voyd of Authority. Who will not now ſtep forth, as <hi>Aphraates,</hi> who lived in the Wilderneſſe all his life: yet once he was found in the ſtreets of <hi>Antioch,</hi> in the daies of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Valens,</hi> when <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> a ſpark at firſt, but being not timely quenched had kindled a fire, that burnt almoſt over all the World? He excuſed the change of his former courſe, by the ſimilitude of a modeſt Virgin, who lurked in the ſecret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of her Fathers Houſe, till it was ſet on fire; but then neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity compelled her to run into the open Streets, to cry out for help to quench the Fire.</p>
            <p>We ſee, by ſad experience, how faſt they faint, and fall from the truth; even <hi>ſtars fall from Heaven;</hi> the <hi>Sun,</hi> as if aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is even now about to bee turned into darkneſſe; and the <hi>Moon</hi> into bloud, (both in one <hi>Month)</hi> as if there were ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in Heaven, for theſe ſadder Eclipſes of the Truth on Earth; or, as if the <hi>laſt times,</hi> that Chriſt foretold, had overtaken us.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Church, (ſuppoſed to be of two thouſand yeares continuance) may be compared to two Dayes; the firſt Day began at the firſt riſing of the Son of Righteouſneſſe; and had for its
<pb facs="tcp:118118:3"/> Morning, <hi>the three firſt Centuries,</hi> till <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> the Noontide, the next; &amp; it continued <hi>the three following Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies;</hi> and there never ſhined more glorious Lights in the Houſe of God; the <hi>Sun</hi> of Learning and Religion, being then in the <hi>Zenith:</hi> but this laſted not long till it declined to an Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; to which are allotted <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>next Centuries;</hi> The Beams grew low, the Light obſcure, and at laſt the World was benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This <hi>firſt Days night</hi> had a more then <hi>Cymmeria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Superſtition:</hi> even <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cals it, <hi>Saeculum infoelix; in quo Scriptores illuſtres nulli; nulla Concilia;</hi> it continued till the Year 1050. The <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> from 850. to 1050. ſhining as a few ſmaller <hi>Stars:</hi> but this <hi>Night</hi> once paſt; the <hi>ſecond Day</hi> began to dawn; and after a ſtrugling twixt light and darknes (which continued two, or three hundred years) the Light of Learning got the better; and then the <hi>ſecond Day</hi> had its Noon: ſoon after the Year 1500. as fair a <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as ever the Earth ſaw, ſince Chriſt: how long that Noon continued, I cannot tell: but ſure I am, this <hi>ſecond Day</hi> is declining towards an <hi>Evening;</hi> the ſhadow of Mount <hi>Athos</hi> reacheth to the Iſle, <hi>Lemnos;</hi> a ſure fore-running toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the going down of the <hi>Sun: Wo be to us; For the Day goeth away; for the ſhadows of the Evening are ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, Jer.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>and hundreds of deeds of Darknes, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Schiſmes, Hereſies, ſwarme together, to uſher in the Worlds laſt Night: and ſaving that God, of his goodneſſe, hath promiſed to cut ſhort this ſecond Day, I think this ſecond Deluge of Sin, &amp; Schiſms, would ſave as few from drowning, as the firſt Deluge did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curteous Reader;</hi> If thou canſt not tell this is truth by thy Experience: then I give God thanks; that there are ſome <hi>Parts</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> not yet infected with this Plague. My <hi>Pariſh</hi> alſo was a Virgin, not invaded, till about a twelve-month ſince; we
<pb facs="tcp:118118:3"/> had ſuch happines as we deſired; and, it ſeems, more then wee deſerved; <hi>when the Grounds about us were wet with ſhowres of Schiſmes: yet wee were dry, with Gideons Fleece;</hi> But becauſe we gave not God thanks, he ſuffered Satan to ſeduce <hi>two Brethren,</hi> by nature, and in iniquity, who began firſt to loath the Manna, that raind down from Heaven, every <hi>Sabaoth day, &amp; luſted after Quailes; ſtrange Doctrines,</hi> that were taught in the <hi>Towns</hi> about us: At length they brought <hi>Mr. Thomſon,</hi> now my Antagoniſt (Father of thoſe Children, that he brings up to pick out their <hi>ſpiritual Parents</hi> Eys) who Preached privately to ſuch of my <hi>Pariſh,</hi> as they could perſwade to come and heare him: Which being without my Conſent, and againſt my Conſcience, I ſhewed ſome diſlike; rather by not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, then openly diſproving any of their Opinions; or their Practices: I durſt not be too bold; their Multitudes were ſuch; and many of them ſo audacious, in affronting Miniſters: yet ſuch offence they tooke (for I gave none) that one of the Brethren (the yonger, but elder in wickednes) went from houſe to houſe, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my Neighbours not to pay me Tithes: but firſt hee uſed all means to get into my debt; hoping to deceive me: and when he had, ſo far, that he had no further hopes, then (to get a Bond, which, God knowes, was none of mine, though taken in my name, and he knew it too) he ſwore, and offered to ſwear ſo fearfully, as would have affrighted any, whoſe conſcience was not cauteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: for he thought I would give, or forgive any thing, rather then oppoſe, or be oppoſed by <hi>Mr. Thomſon.</hi> All the Week he laboured to draw others from hearing me on the Sabaoth: they threatned to pull me out of the Pulpit; the loſſe of my Living; my Eſtate; nay, little leſſe then my Life was threatned; ſo that I durſt ſcarce goe out of my own doors; they ſlandred all the Sermons I Preacht; and when I writ almoſt every word, that I might be ſure nothing ſlipt from me, they did no leſſe detract,
<pb facs="tcp:118118:4"/> and defame me, then before: If I uſed the name of a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, or Sectary; it was them I meant; nay, I durſt ſcarce ſpeak againſt the Divell; if I did; my words were wreſted oftentimes, or alwayes, to that I never thought. I ſaid once, that <hi>Chriſt gave the Devils leave to enter into a heard of Swine;</hi> and they applyed that to themſelves: If I ſpake of any, that were like to go to the Devill; it was reported, that I meant it of them: as if none, but our <hi>Univerſaliſts,</hi> were like to go to the Devill: <hi>Thus every day they wreſted my words; all their thoughts were againſt me for evill, Pſal.</hi> 56. 5.</p>
            <p>They ſet their Children, and Servants to diſturb me in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Preaching, and to trouble the Aſſembly; that either they might not heare, or I might not ſpeake: One of theſe two Brethren ſtayed to heare me in the Morning; and gave infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the other Brethren in the Afternoone: Sometimes he came to my houſe, and called me <hi>Maſter,</hi> as if he meant <hi>to kiſſe mee;</hi> when the <hi>Judas</hi> had an intent <hi>to betray me;</hi> and to be the utter ruine of me, and mine.</p>
            <p>When they waxed worſe, and wickeder ſtill: I moved a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Mr. <hi>T.</hi> in private; publickly I durſt not meet: But that being denied, I ſent a Letter to a <hi>Worthy Gentleman, Juſtice of Peace,</hi> entreating him to tell Mr. <hi>T.</hi> I deſired a friendly Diſcourſe with him in writing: but for this boldnes they gave out ſuch fearfull words againſt me, as have been ſeldome heard: The Brethren met about it, &amp; after ſome ſober co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (I judge charitably) they drew up a <hi>Charge of high Treaſon, committed by Mr.</hi> Wetherall, <hi>againſt the Crown, Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Love, Goodnes, and Soveraignty of the Son of God; for that I denyed Univerſall Redemption, Free Will, and other falſe Opinions; which they calld Truth:</hi> To prove this Charge, they empanell a Jury of 12. Places in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but the Verdict is ungiven up; for they applyed not one
<pb facs="tcp:118118:4"/> Place, to prove any thing; but deſiring ſimply to believe, left it to the conſideration of Rationall men: And after many ſhameleſs ſlaunders, (as their maner is) and threatnings, what they meant to do againſt me, this Charge was ſigned by Mr. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> and ſent abroad among the Brethren; walking without a paſſe, till it was weary, fainted, and could travell no further; for it began to be torne all in pieces, even covered with greaſe and dirt: and then 4 <hi>unruly Fellows</hi> came with it into our Church, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28. a <hi>Smith,</hi> a <hi>Miller,</hi> a <hi>Thatcher,</hi> a <hi>Thraſher;</hi> For their Countrey, they came from the 4 <hi>Windes;</hi> 4 ſeverall Towns, far aſunder; But for their Maners, ſure more barbarous, then He that ſent them: Four Beaſts would have been more civill, than they, in Sermon time; immediately after Sermon they brought forth their <hi>Charge;</hi> the <hi>Smith</hi> diſcharged it; and they all char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me, with preaching falſe Doctrine that Day; they forgat what I had ſaid, and remembred only what they were ſent to ſay.</p>
            <p>I thought it not fit to tempt God in truſting my ſelfe among ſuch: ſo I left them, without anſwering either to their Words, or their beaſtly Behaviour; but my Neighbours were amaz'd: They ſpake, and did on ſuch a manner, that Children will remember, when they are old; and Old men would never have forgot, had they ſeene the like, ſince they were Children.</p>
            <p>But when they ſaw my Neighbours were not pleas'd; nay, heartily diſpleas'd at their Behaviours; They went inſtantly and informed the other Brethren, who came together, about, or above 30. before Night; and concluded a generall Meeting at our Town, on Thurſday after; they menac'd, as if they meant a War againſt me, and my Neighbours; gave out Mr. <hi>T.</hi> ſhould teach at my Door; Their Words were ſo high, that I might well fear the pulling down of my Houſe, or the pulling out of my Houſe: but it came only to a Chair, or a Chimney Buſineſs; and ſo <hi>the Town Clerke diſmiſſed the Aſſembly, Acts</hi> 19. 41.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118118:5"/>
            <p> Therefore, when I ſaw the danger I lived in every day; and how they went from evill, to worſe; I reſolved upon a Diſcourſe againſt ſome of their Opinions, and their Practiſes, for better ſatisfaction of my owne People, over whom God had given mee the Charge: If peradventure I might ſhew it to ſome few of my Friends, was the top of my intent. I began <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. and ended before <hi>Jan.</hi> the laſt: but when I ſhewed it to my Neighbours, next Sabaoth after I had made an end, never furious Lions were more fierce, then the <hi>Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Siſters,</hi> becauſe I durſt bee ſo bold beyond their expectation: their <hi>words</hi> were <hi>intollerable; their writings incredible,</hi> but that I have them by me, ſent to my houſe to incenſe me; and ſhewed to any that would ſee them, to ſhame me, by <hi>John Hatfield,</hi> one of the two Brothers I ſpake of before; a man whom malice hath made to ride, and go many miles, to doe me miſchiefes: <hi>They cried not out againſt</hi> Paul <hi>at Epheſus, Acts</hi> 19. more, then theſe men did againſt me; as if I were unworthy to live, for writing that which <hi>(Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader)</hi> I here preſent to publick view; being compelled to take this courſe, partly out of pitty towards the poore ſeduced people: and in part to recover my own Credit: their Words may leave a skar, if the wound be cured: Silence in ſuch Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is a crying ſin: Every man, but moſt of all Miniſters, are bound to diſcharge themſelves from all imputations; eſpecially of falſe <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Hereſie;</hi> wherewith I have been charged openly: a Crime which Water cannot waſh away; it hath been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually burnt out with Fire: It leaveth ſuch a ſpot in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that <hi>Cyprian</hi> conceiveth the bloud of Martyrdome can not fetch it out: I hope I have made it appeare plainly, whether our <hi>Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> or their <hi>Pelagianiſme</hi> be <hi>falſe Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Hereſie:</hi> Here is a <hi>Salve</hi> to cure the <hi>biting</hi> of theſe <hi>Serpents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solinus</hi> writeth that in <hi>Sardinia,</hi> where there is a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="tcp:118118:5"/> Serpent, called <hi>Solifuga,</hi> whoſe bitting is preſent death; yet there is alſo at hand <hi>a Fountaine,</hi> in which they who waſh themſelves are inſtantly cured: and ſo if any of my Neighbours be now bitten by theſe <hi>Solifuga's,</hi> theſe Serpents, here is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy at hand; the Antidote may be there ready, where the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction firſt breakes out.</p>
            <p>We run to the Phyſitian to cure the Diſeaſes of our bodies: but the Diſeaſes of our ſoules are far more dangerous, we ought to have a greater care to cure them: even the bruite Beaſts, that have no underſtanding, will teach us ſo much providence. The <hi>Harts</hi> of <hi>Creete,</hi> or <hi>Candy,</hi> as we now call it, being wounded with an arrow, will run to ſeek ſome Dictamnie, which (they ſay) doth pull the arrow out, and heale the wound. The <hi>Swallows,</hi> to cure the blindneſſe of their yong ones Eyes, flie to fetch <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landine,</hi> which reſtores their ſight: The <hi>Dog,</hi> when he is ſick, haſts to his <hi>Graſſe,</hi> to give himſelfe a Vomit: The <hi>Toade,</hi> fighting with the <hi>Spider,</hi> as ſoon as ſhe feels her ſelfe begin to ſwell, crawleth to her <hi>Plantaine,</hi> and ſo is recovered: even <hi>the Stork in the Heaven knoweth her time; the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and the Crane, Jer.</hi> 8. 7. and they make uſe of their time: but we poor miſerable men; more unreaſonable then bruit Beaſts, are wounded ſpiritually every day, many times deadly; and yet ſeldome ſeek for medicines to cure the maladies of our ſouls. I know, the Means I offer unto thee, gentle Reader, is very ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſo they muſt be, my ſelfe being even a Child in underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but being in the dark, a Child with a Lanthorn and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle lighted, is better then a Man that hath a Torch, if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted: now in all theſe 4. or 5. years, that they have roved in our corner of the Country, I heard of none that made day reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or did, or durſt ſay, Sir, Why doe you ſo? The feare of <hi>Captaine T.</hi> and <hi>his Troops</hi> did ſhake ſome Miniſters, and many other men beſides, like a Fever, or <hi>as the Trees of the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118118:6"/> 
               <hi>Foreſt are ſhaken with the Wind:</hi> Therefore rather then Gods Cauſe ſhould ſuſtaine ſuch damage, as I ſaw it did, by a general ſilence, I ſtept forth, like the <hi>Lacedemonian Soldiour,</hi> impotent of his legs, and neither meet to fight, nor to flie; yet had he this hope, that he might blunt the edge of his Enemies ſwords; and ſet on, or make others aſhamed, that were more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fight: <hi>Silver and Gold have I none, but Goats hair, or Rammes skins, or ſuch as I have, I give, to cover the Tabernacle of my God:</hi> It pitied mee, to ſee the Sheepe of Chriſt, like Wolves, ſwallow down whole whatſoever was put into their mouthes by ſuch Carvers: and if I gain, or beget but one Soule, it will be ſome comfort to me; That one, in time, may beget another; and that other, another; and ſo I may bee a means to beget many Soules to God. I ſhall pray (as it is my part) that my poore paines may profit thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> and prevaile to the beating down of Sinnes, and Schiſmes; which God grant, for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake, our only Lord and Saviour; It ſhall be in the dayly devotions of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Brother in Chriſt, <hi>JOHN WETHERALL</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>In pag. 4. line 17. for Earth, read Church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118118:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Diſcovery, and Confutation of the Opinions, and Practiſes of ſome falſe Brethren,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch as are Adverſaries to the Truth, ſlaunder our Doctrine touching <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination</hi> and <hi>Free Will;</hi> as if thereby we led men to bee careleſſe in their lives; becauſe (as they urge it) God having <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated</hi> all things, mans <hi>Free Will</hi> is loſt thereby; ſo that he can not doe otherwiſe then he doth, but God himſelfe (by our Doctrine) muſt be the Authour of ſinne: Wherein they ſhew their unſatiable deſire of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, &amp; that beſides the Grave, the barren Womb, the Earth, &amp; the Fire, which are never ſatisfied, <hi>Pro.</hi> 30. 15. There is yet a fifth thing, as unſatiable as they; that is, the Contentious Spirit of an Adverſary, never ſatisfied with lying and contradiction. For, let them ſay directly what they miſlike, Is it our Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination?</hi> Yea, (beſides that, it is the Profeſſion of all the Proteſtant Churches) you ſhall ſee it preſently proved by one, who is able to ſay the leaſt of ten thouſand. Is it becauſe we deny <hi>Free Will?</hi> Yea, they bely their owne knowledge, they know we deny it but in part; <hi>In ſtatu integro,</hi> it was Free, <hi>in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118118:7"/> 
               <hi>laeſo,</hi> it is Free from conſtraint. Is it becauſe we teach God is the Authour of ſinne? Even the Jeſuits excuſe us; the Proteſtants know well (ſaith <hi>Suarez)</hi> that God intendeth not that <note place="margin">Opuſe lib. 2. cap. 2.</note> which is <hi>formall</hi> in ſinne, nor inclineth the Will of man, that he ſhould intend it. Or is it finally, becauſe we hold ſome fatall neceſſity, conſtraining the Will of man, that he cannot doe otherwiſe then he doth? That ſo all care and conſultation ſhould be to no purpoſe: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome of the old Philoſophers, and new Mahumetans tell ſuch Tales, but we teach the contrary.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like, being malicious and baſe imputations, deviſed by men in their fury, and deſperate adventures againſt us, to ſeduce the ignorant, and make our Cauſe odious, which even their owne people would embrace, if they knew it. And my ſelfe being threatned (by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ignorant men of meane condition) ſet on by others, not onely with the loſſe of my Living, but (I may almoſt ſay) of my life; beſides the ſlaunders caſt upon me by ſuch as can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe: I am forced therefore to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for my ſelfe, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other Reformed Proteſtant Churches; againſt Pelagians, Papiſts, Arminians, Univerſaliſts.</p>
            <p>I have read of a ſtudious Father, who medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating very much upon the Myſtery of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, there appeared unto him a Childe, that with a Shell, was lading the Sea into a little hole; he demanded of the Child what he was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118118:7"/> about to doe, I intend (ſayd the Childe) to empty all the Ocean into this Pit; it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for thee (ſayd the Father) as poſſible (the Childe replyed) as for thee to comprehend this profound Myſtery in thy ſhallow capacity: <hi>De me nunc narratur fabula,</hi> and this is the Caſe of the moſt able men in theſe deepe Divine Myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simonides</hi> being asked by <hi>Hiero</hi> King of <hi>Sicily,</hi> what God was? he deſired a day to deliberate, &amp; then being asked again, he deſired two daies, and being asked again, he deſired four daies; and ever as he was asked, he gave no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but deſired to have the dayes doubled: but double and triple daies and yeares, yet that time is no time for ſuch an undertaking.</p>
            <p>For the men of this World to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to tell what God did, even before there was one man or a world, is but a deſperate adventure, even beyond the Gyants of old: but it is able to make any mans heart ake, and his haire ſtand upright, to heare how our ignorant people prate as boldly, as if they had beene by, and ſay—what they ſay, concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, unſearchable Decree of our Great God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, if any man liſt to heare, he may, for they will ſpeake that which I may not write. For my owne part, in this myſterious point of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> I could have choſen rather to aſcend by Repentance, New Obedience, Good Workes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then deſcend, diving into, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining Gods Decree: For I know that in the true Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> we ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118118:8"/> reaſon rather <hi>aſcendendo,</hi> then <hi>deſcendendo:</hi> thus I live in obedience to God, in love with my Neighbour; I follow my Vocation honeſtly, and therefore I truſt that God hath <hi>Elected</hi> and <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> mee to ſalvation; not thus (which is the uſuall courſe of Argument) God hath <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> and choſen me to life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though I ſinne never ſo grievouſly, yet I ſhall not be damned: For whom he once love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, hee loveth to the end. I ſay that this is the right manner of reaſoning, in the point of <hi>Predeſtination:</hi> But unleſſe we will ſuffer our people to be led (I verily believe they will be loth to let me tell the manner how they are led) I muſt declare my conſcience, to cleare my ſelf, that it is none of my fault, if any perſevere, and periſh in this rent, now new made in the Earth, through which they may as eaſily fall into Hell, as <hi>Korah,</hi> and his Company, did through that rent in the Earth: therefore with as great a care as I can to avoyd Preſumption, I proceed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, touching <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> we hold, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">Rom. 9. Eph. 1. 4 5. 1. Theſ 5. Acts 2. 23. 2. Tim. 2. 20.</note> to the Scriptures, that God from all Eternity, before the world was made, hath not onely fore-ſeene all things, that could be, or ſhould be by his appointment or permiſſion; but alſo by an unchangeable Decree, hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained all things and perſons, to certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate ends, for his owne Glory; and that neither the Saints were elected in Chriſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible and perſevering Grace, and eternall Glory for their fore-ſeene righteouſneſſe; nor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118118:8"/> the Reprobates refuſed, or non-elected for their fore-ſeene wickedneſſe; but both the one and the other were <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> to thoſe their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Eſtates, according to the Councel of Gods owne Will, which was not mooved by any thing hee foreſaw in the parties, but hee moſt freely Decreed according to his own pleaſure, &amp; abſolute dominion that he hath over the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And this Decree of Gods Will is the firſt mover of all other wills, and things in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; whereupon the ſmalleſt, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent, or caſuall things that fall out, depend as upon their Univerſall Cauſe; whoſe influence into the ſecond cauſes, directeth, produceth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth, and ordinateth them to their effects; not by enforcing them by any conſtraint, but by enclining them to worke according to their owne condition, ſo as the ſayd effects proceed out of them, according to their own natures, a contingent effect of a contingent cauſe, and a free effect out of a voluntary and free cauſe.</p>
            <p>This is the ſum of that Doctrine, which the Reformed Proteſtant Churches hold, touching <hi>Predeſtination:</hi> They place the Decree of God to order all things, for his own glory, as it is, Pro. 16. 4. which is the end, before the meanes, that is, before Creation, the Fall, Redemption, &amp;c. but the Pelagians, Papiſts, Arminians, Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaliſts, place the means before the end; as for example; theſe ſay, <hi>Mediatio Chriſti eſt Cauſa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>externe movens, reſpectu volitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis divinae in Electionis actu;</hi> that is, the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118118:9"/> of Chriſt is the externall cauſe moving the will of God in the act of Election; whereas the Reformed Churches ſay, that the will of God is the ſole cauſe of the mediation of Chriſt: Chriſt is not ſubordinate to the very Decree it ſelfe of Election, he is to the Execution thereof, as it appears, 1 Pet. 1. 20.</p>
            <p>Thus in the diſtribution of the cauſes of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Damnation, our Adverſaries turne them upſide downe; for they feigue a generall decree in God,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To create man.</item>
               <item>2. To give a Law to his Creature, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of life and death.</item>
               <item>3. To permit the fall.</item>
               <item>4. To redeeme all mankinde in Chriſt, hence Univerſall Election.</item>
               <item>5. To call all mankinde ſo redeemed, hence Univerſall Vocation.</item>
               <item>6. Upon their Faith or Infidelity he fixeth his Decree.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, ſay they, God propounded equally to himſelfe <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and loved the one no more then the other; ſecondly, he purpoſed to ſave him of the two that ſhould do well, and damn him of the two that ſhould do ill; thirdly, he Decreed to give them both ſufficient means of ſalvation, whereby <hi>Eſau</hi> may as well be ſaved as <hi>Jacob:</hi> fourthly, he Decreed to leave them both to the liberty of their owne Free-will, to uſe, or not to uſe the means: fiftly, he foreſaw <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> would, <hi>Eſau</hi> would not uſe the means: ſixthly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118118:9"/> hereupon he pronounced the Decree of Election to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of Reprobation to <hi>Eſau:</hi> thus Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, Papiſts, Arminians, Univerſaliſts.</p>
            <p>Theſe two laſt, Remonſtrants (ſo the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans call them, and the name offends them not) for this Sect peſter'd them parts firſt, and gave occaſion to the States of the United Provinces to aſſemble that Synod at <hi>Dort;</hi> whither (at their inſtance) came religious and learned men from other Reformed Churches; as out of England, Biſhop <hi>Carleton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Davenant,</hi> Doctor <hi>Ward,</hi> Doctour <hi>Goade,</hi> Doctor <hi>Belcanquell,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, theſe Remonſtrants that oppoſe our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> (being of the ſame minde with them that defend Univerſal Redemption:) they ſay thus: I'le uſe their owne words: <hi>Deum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ameſius de Elect. pag. 11.</note> 
               <hi>aeterno &amp; immutabili decreto, in Jeſu Chriſto filio ſuo, ante jactum mundi fundamentum, ſtatuiſſe, ex lapſo &amp; peccatis obnoxio humano genere; ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in Chriſto, propter Chriſtum, &amp; per Chriſtum ſervare, qui Spiritus Sancti gratia, in eundem Filium ejus cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt; &amp; in ea fide, fidei<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> obedientia, per eandem gratiam, uſque ad finem perſeverant:</hi> that is, God in his eternall, and immutable Decree, in Jeſus Chriſt his Son, before the foundation of the world, did determine, out of lapſed mankinde, to ſave thoſe in Chriſt, for Chriſt, and by Chriſt, who by the ſpirit did believe in that his Sonne, and perſevere in that faith, and obedience of faith, by grace, unto their lives end.</p>
            <p>Now in this Theſis of theirs, are theſe five
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118118:10"/> things. 1. The Act, or Decree it ſelfe: 2. the Object: 3. the End: 4. the Condition: 5. the Foundation. Firſt, the Act or Decree it ſelfe, and that, they ſay, is two fold: 1. Generall, by which God Decreed to ſave all that would believe and perſevere: the 2. Particular, by which hee did Decree to ſave certaine perſons, whom he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw would certainly beleeve, and perſevere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end: ſome of them call theſe two, Gods Antecedent, &amp; Conſequent Will; or <hi>generale &amp; particulare pronuntiatum:</hi> Thus they make, you may ſee, two Wills in God, againſt the Spirit of God, which ſaith, God is in one mind, <hi>Job.</hi> 23. 23. The ſecond thing conſiderable in their Theſis, is the Object of this Decree, which (they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſſe) all the members of Chriſt are not; they cannot tell how to include Infants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want faith, and perſeverance; nay, they include in the Object of this Decree, onely ſuch as have lived, and perſevered, all other are excluded that are yet alive, untill they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the end; ſo that by this Opinion, they muſt firſt have Faith and Perſeverance, before God can fix his Decree; which is a fearfull thing to affirme, for ſo they are not <hi>Pre-deſtinated,</hi> but <hi>Poſt-deſtinated,</hi> they are forc'd therefore to a further abſurdity; that is, to diſtinguiſh betwixt an incompleat, which (they ſay) is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the faithfull, and a compleat Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is proper only to ſuch as perſevere. The third thing to be conſidered in their Theſis, is the End of this Decree, and that (they ſay) is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118118:10"/> ſalvation and glory; contrary to the expreſſe words of Scripture, which ſaith not we are <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> to Glory onely, but alſo to Holineſſe, or a godly life, and to the Grace of Adoption, before we can attain to Glory; as it is plaine, Eph. 1. 4. 5. He hath choſen us in him before the Foundation of the World, that we ſhould be Holy, &amp;c. In the Decree of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> there is firſt What, 2. by What, 3. to What: the firſt, Man, the 2. Grace, the 3. a Godly Life, and after it is ended, Eternall Glory. The 4. thing is the Condition required in this Decree of theirs; wee ſay it is the Good Pleaſure, or the Will of God, without any Condition; wee are <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Good Pleaſure of his Will, Eph. 1. 5. But the Condition in their <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is fore-ſeen Faith and Works: <hi>Tenendum ex Scripturis veram Converſionem, praeſtationem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bonorum operum eſſe conditiones praerequiſitas ante Juſtificationem:</hi> That is, we hold true <hi>Converſion,</hi> and <hi>Good Works,</hi> to be Conditions required before <hi>Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Arminius</hi> in that Epiſtle before his Diſcourſe on <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. And <hi>Nic. Grevincho.</hi> is of the ſame minde; he ſeekes to prove it out of the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> I have fought a good fight, &amp;c. But if <hi>Good works</hi> be Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required before <hi>Juſtification,</hi> then it follows, they are required before <hi>Election;</hi> there is one and the ſame Cauſe of both: Thus they even out God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty from having any hand in his own Decree, and put all into the power of foreſeen <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Workes,</hi> whereas the Scriptures ſay, that we are not <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> for <hi>Faith,</hi> but to <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Good Workes,</hi> as I ſhall prove afterward. The fifth thing in this Decree of theirs, is the Foundation, that, they ſay, is Chriſt, and ſo do we; but in this we differ: they call Chriſt the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118118:11"/> externall Cauſe moving God to make this Decree of <hi>Election;</hi> whereas we ſay, the Will of God onely, was the Cauſe why Chriſt became our Mediator, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; the Mediation or Redemption of Chriſt was not the Cauſe of the Will of God. Thus the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie betwixt the Remonſtrants, or Univerſalliſts, and the Reformed Proteſtant Churches about <hi>Election,</hi> was ſtated at the Synod of <hi>Dort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Theſis of the Remonſtrants, or ſuch as hold Univerſall Redemption, at the ſame time (which they would have defended againſt the Reformed) was this: <hi>Proinde Jeſus Chriſtus pro omnibus &amp; ſingulis mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us eſt, atque id ita quidem, ut omnibus per mortem crucis, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliationem, &amp; peccatorum remiſſionem impetravit, ea tamen conditione, ut nemo illa peccatorum remiſſione fruatur, praeter hominem fidelem. Ameſ. de Redemp. pag.</hi> 116. That is, the Remonſtrants or Univerſaliſts furthermore affirme, that Jeſus Chriſt died for all, and every one, and that ſo as he obtayned Reconciliation, and Remiſſion of Sins for all, but on this Condition, that none obtain this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or Reconciliation, but the Faithfull.</p>
            <p>I might open this Theſis of Redemption, as I did that other of Election, but it is ſo plaine I need not: the Sum of the Controverſie betwixt the Proteſtant Churches, and Remonſtrants, or (as wee call them) Univerſaliſts, came to this, or to theſe three Heads: 1. whether by the Death of Chriſt there was an Impetration, which had no Application: 2. whether this Impetration did equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong to All: 3. that none had this Impetration of Chriſt certainly applied, or to be applied to them in the Eternall Counſell of God; but God had <hi>Deſtinated</hi> his Son to death, before hee had <hi>Deſtinated</hi> any to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118118:11"/> by his Death: and this Grace of Chriſts Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was (as it were) ſpread abroad in the ayre, indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to any, every man might catch it that could by Faith. Theſe men ſeem to feign to themſelves a Grace, as it were ſome garment hanging in the ayre, which every man may put on that will; but theſe be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of mans wiſedome: the holy Scriptures ſpeake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, <hi>Pet. Mart. part.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 51. as tranſlated by <hi>Ant. Marten.</hi> Theſe things the Remonſtrants or Univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts affirmed; and all theſe the Reformed Proteſtant party denied.</p>
            <p>Now from theſe Opinions, that <hi>Predeſtination</hi> was not the Decree of God, to Elect ſome, and paſſe by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that God had certainly Elected none, but upon Condition; That Chriſt died for all, and every one, &amp;c. I ſay from theſe Abſurdities it followes:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 1. Firſt, that God would have All men, that is, every particular man to be ſaved, contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for if God will have all to be ſaved, wherefore are they not ſaved? Will God have all to be ſaved, and can he not have his Will? This Opinion is againſt the Omnipotency of God; by it, Gods abſolute Will, the Will of his good Pleaſure may be defeated, and not accompliſhed, which is a deſperate ſhift, contrary to the truth, flat oppoſite to the word of God, which ſaith, our God hath done whatſoever pleaſed him in Heaven and Earth, Pſal. 135. 6. who hath reſiſted his Will? Rom. 9. 19. God is in one minde, who can turn him? and what his ſoule deſireth, that he doth, Job 23. 13. Indeed the Declarative or Revealed Will of God is not alwaies fulfilled, but his Abſolute Will and Good Pleaſure is alwaies fullfilled; a Chriſtian, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118118:12"/> in the Principles of Religion, cannot make the Impotency of mans will to prevaile againſt the Omnipotency of God, or conceive his purpoſe may be diſappointed, or his Abſolute Will fruſtrated by any thing in us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 2. Secondly, it follows from theſe Opinions, that there is an Univerſall Election, of all, and every man; a witleſſe conceit: for if all men Univerſally be appointed to Grace, then there is no Election, or Choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſome; he cannot be ſaid to Elect, that Chooſeth all: and if onely ſome bee appointed to <hi>Grace,</hi> (as it muſt needs be in <hi>Election,)</hi> then is not <hi>Grace</hi> Univerſall: it is flat againſt the word of God; for Chriſt avoucheth plainly, that fewer are choſen then called, Mat. 22. 14. He ſaith moreover, that all which are given him ſhall be one with him, and have life everlaſting, John 17. 2. 11. But all men ſhall not be one with him, and have life everlaſting; therefore all are not given to Chriſt of God the Father: all mens names are not written in the Booke of life, Apoc. 20. 15. the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is not prepared for all, Mat. 25. 35. Chriſt never knew ſome, Mat. 7. 23. And whereas they build <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Election</hi> upon the largeneſſe of the <hi>Promiſe, if they believe;</hi> upon the like ground they may as well make an <hi>Univerſall Decree</hi> of Reprobation, whereby God De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees all men to bee damned indefinitely, <hi>if they doe not believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 3. Thirdly, it followes, that there is an <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Vocation;</hi> for <hi>Univerſall Grace</hi> hath theſe three parts, <hi>Univerſall Election, Univerſall Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Vocation,</hi> which is quite oppoſite to the word of God; for from the Creation till Chriſt, one part of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118118:12"/> world was a People, and received into the Covenant; the other (and that the greateſt part of the world) was no People, and out of the Covenant. The Church at firſt was ſhut up in the Families of the Patriarchs, and in the Family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> it was entailde on <hi>Iſaac:</hi> the world afterward was divided into the <hi>Jew,</hi> a Church; and the <hi>Gentile,</hi> no Church, till the comming of Chriſt: therefore it is, that the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> called the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Priſoners, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 9. <hi>Hoſea</hi> calls the Gentiles a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that had obtained no mercy at all, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 23. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that in times paſt the Gentiles were not eſteemed a People, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. Chriſt denied the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> the Requeſt for her Daughter, upon this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; it is not meet to take the Childrens bread and caſt it to Dogs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 26. If any object, that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles fell away from the Covenant; I anſwer, grant that of the Fathers, yet their Children never heard of the Covenant; therefore it is that the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith of the Gentiles, that neither God knew them, nor did they know God, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55. 5. Univerſaliſt, I pray thee ſpeake in earneſt, how could the <hi>Americans, Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals,</hi> and other Savadges have any Call? No, Pelagian, it is not Nature: No, Semi-Pelagian, it is not Grace and Nature; we cannot ſo much as thinke a good thought, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. I conclude hence no Univerſall Call.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 4. Fourthly, it followes from this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Univerſall Redemption, &amp;c.</hi> that God is all Mercy, and nothing elſe; whereas the ſoveraigne end of all Gods Actions is anſwerable to his Nature, which is not Mercy and Love alone, but Juſtice alſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right End of mans Creation is the manifeſtation of Gods Glory, both in Juſtice and Mercy; ſearch the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118118:13"/> Scriptures, and ſee if Juſtice alſo be not an Attribute of our God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 5. Fiftly, hence it followes that <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is for fore-ſeene Faith and Workes; unleſſe Gods Preſcience diſcover ſomething, his <hi>Predeſtination</hi> Decrees nothing, but after the fore-ſight of Faith and Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and the former Gift of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> to Glory, muſt depend upon a later Gift of Faith, quite contrary to the Word of God; for either it is Gods will the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſhall have Grace, and the Reprobates no Grace given them; or elſe they believe, or not believe of their own Free Will; this later is groſſe Pelagianiſme, making Nature the beginning of Grace, and if the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be granted, that God fore-ſees no Grace, but what himſelfe <hi>Predeſtinates</hi> to give; nor no ſin, but what up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the witholding of his Grace, the Reprobate will free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke, then it followes that God will and doth give Grace, becauſe firſt he hath elected; and will give no Grace, becauſe he hath reprobated, and there is no cauſe of either, but Gods owne Will; no fore-ſeen Faith or Workes. Againe I reaſon thus, the End is alwayes in intention, before the Meanes, <hi>primus intentione, ultimus executione,</hi> but Gods Will to elect men to Glory, is the End; therefore Gods Will to elect men to Glory goes before his Will to give them Faith and Grace; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he Elects not after, or upon the fore-ſight of Faith and Grace; therefore before he ſee Faith or Grace in <hi>Jacob,</hi> which he will give him, he purpoſes to give him Life Eternall: But theſe men will give God their Faith and Good Workes in lieu of their Redemption by Chriſt, againſt <hi>Iſay.</hi> 52. 3. <hi>&amp; Rom.</hi> 11. 35. I know they diſtinguiſh 'twixt the Antecedent, and Conſequent Wil
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118118:13"/> of God, Gods Antecedent Will to ſave every man, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though conſidering the ſinnes of men, he hath a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Will to condemne ſome: But this diſtinction makes the matter more abſurd, and ſalves it not; for God is immutable, his Will is one as he is one; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he fore ſaw in any that himſelfe purpoſed to worke; if he foreſaw Grace, and the good uſe of <hi>Free Will</hi> in <hi>Jacob,</hi> he purpoſed to worke it by infuſing it; what have we, that we have not received? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. Every good and every perfect gift is from above, <hi>James</hi> 1. 17. If he foreſaw Sinne, and the ill uſe of <hi>Free Will</hi> in <hi>Eſau,</hi> he purpoſed to worke it alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 13. 18. by witholding Grace and hardening; and he not onely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Worke that which he foreſaw, but to Worke and Effect it, as the Means, and as a ſubordinate Second Cauſe, to bring man to the End apoynted: from hence it follows that Faith, Workes, &amp;c. are onely Meanes ordained by God to bring us to the End, not Cauſes of our Election. I cannot tell how they can avoid the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts <hi>Meritum è congruo,</hi> and plaine Pelagianiſme, that maintaine foreſeen <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Works;</hi> for thus ſaith <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius: Licet non ſecundum merita bonorum Operum, tamenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum merita bonae voluntatis datur gratia, &amp; ratio Pelagii eſt; alioqui Deus eſſet Acceptor perſonarum, ſi ſine ullis praece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus meritis cujus vult miſeretur:</hi> That is, though Grace bee not given according to the Merit of our <hi>Good Workes,</hi> yet it is given according to the Merit of our <hi>Good Will;</hi> &amp; the Reaſon <hi>Pelagius</hi> renders, is this, elſe God ſhould be a Reſpecter of Perſons, if he have mercy on whom he will, without regard of foregoing Merits; ſo that they are Cozens not far off, if they be not neare Cozens to Papiſts and Pelagians, that defend foreſeen Faith, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118118:14"/> Workes; all of them anſwer one another, even as the Eccho doth the Voyce, and they will waſh away theſe blots, when the Blackmore changeth his skin. <hi>Pelagius Redivivus</hi> is now no newes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 6. Sixtly, hence followes <hi>Free Will;</hi> I know they ſay that Gods Grace muſt goe along with our Will; but this excuſe is onely a Vaile or Vizard, which hides their Pelagian faces, that the ignorant People might not ſee them; ſo that (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of the like words uſed by the Pelagians) we would receive them without ſcruple, but that they ſpeak them, whoſe meaning is well enough known unto us: <hi>Initium Fidei, &amp; Converſionis deſiderium eſt ex nobis, incrementum a Gratia:</hi> the beginning of Faith, and the deſire of Converſion, is of our ſelves; the increaſe, of Grace: <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitrium eſt ad hoc liberum, ut velit, vel nolit admittere medicinam:</hi> the Will is free to will, or nill the admiſſion of the Medicine, ſo ſay the Pelagians; and the Arminians and our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaliſts ſay, Gods Grace muſt go along with our <hi>Free Will:</hi> he hath a good wit that can diſtinguiſh betwixt theſe two. I have read of one <hi>Melitides</hi> a naturall foole, who could not tell whether his Mother or his Father brought him forth; ſo theſe men cannot tell, whether God begets them to himſelfe, or their owne <hi>Free Will</hi> begets them unto God. I ſay therefore, that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines mans Will, and yet it is Free ſtill; Gods Will is above ours, flowes into it, and moves it, and yet the Will followes the dictate of its owne Intellect; is freed onely from Conſtraint, not from Neceſſity, from which the Will of Angels is not free, for they can do no evill, they can doe nothing but that which is good. And as a man, by a device, ſhould let Birds flye, and yet cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118118:14"/> them all to goe to ſuch a place, as himſelfe would, ſo doth God rule the <hi>Will:</hi> The Spirit of God, at firſt, findes nothing in the <hi>Will,</hi> to helpe his <hi>Grace,</hi> in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of a Sinner: <hi rend="margQuotes">Firſt, <hi>Grace</hi> gives life to the dead <hi>Will,</hi> and then the <hi>Will</hi> being revived, becomes an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of God, both to apprehend his <hi>Grace</hi> offered, and to worke forward with it;</hi> but this by the Seede of <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>New Life,</hi> that God hath put into it, not by the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>mans Will:</hi> and as my <hi>Paper,</hi> whereon I am writing, retaines the <hi>Inke paſſively,</hi> and brings no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of its owne to the writing, but being written on, it becommeth an Inſtrument with me of the writing; ſo is it in the <hi>Will</hi> of man at his <hi>Converſion.</hi> It is God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that doth <hi>juſtifie, Rom.</hi> 8. 33. For it is he onely <hi>that forgiveth ſins, Eſa.</hi> 43. 25. It is he only, that can by make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us righteous in Chriſt, gives us right and title to the Kingdome of Heaven: It is no <hi>action</hi> therefore of <hi>our owne,</hi> or of any <hi>Creature,</hi> neither is it wrought by <hi>our owne Preparations</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions.</hi> For although every man is bound to uſe all Meanes, to attaine to <hi>Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Yet it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy, Rom.</hi> 9. 16. For if God bee the <hi>Agent</hi> in <hi>juſtifying</hi> us, then are We the <hi>Patients:</hi> and for that cauſe we are never in the Scriptures exhorted to <hi>juſtification,</hi> or to the parts thereof (which are not our <hi>officia,</hi> or duties, but Gods <hi>beneficia,</hi> or bleſſings) as we are to the duties of <hi>ſanctification,</hi> whereunto we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already <hi>juſtified,</hi> and <hi>regenerated,</hi> doe cooperate with the <hi>Spirit of Grace; If the Sonne have made us free, wee ſhall be free indeed, Rom.</hi> 8. 36. We are made free, for of our ſelves we are the ſervants of ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 18. 20. Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is it to aſcribe too little, then too much to <hi>Free Will.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118118:15"/> if I offend, be it rather in giving more to <hi>Gods Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſur.</hi> 7. Seventhly, hence it follows, that <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is mutable, all things being forelaid, which are neceſſary &amp; ſufficient for <hi>perſeverance,</hi> it remaineth ſtill in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of man, to <hi>perſevere,</hi> or not to <hi>perſevere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bertius</hi> in his Booke of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to prove this bold (I had almoſt ſaid blaſphemous) Aſſertion by divers Texts of Scripture: <hi>Non eſſe homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num alios ad vitam, alios ad mortem, aut perditionem deputatos; ſed de ſalute ad perditionem, &amp; de perditione ad ſalutem tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ire poſſe,</hi> there are not any particulars appoynted to life or death, but they may paſſe from either ſtate to the other, ſayd <hi>Pelagius;</hi> and <hi>numerus Electorum poteſt augeri, ac minui,</hi> the number of the Elect may be leſſe, or more, ſayd <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evincho. Theſ. exhibit. pag.</hi> 137. Then <hi>Paul</hi> may, or may not be ſaved, and whoſoever is <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> is but contingently <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> if he perſevere; then the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour to the Hebrewes is out, where he ſaith, <hi>the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God is immutable.</hi> Heb. 6. 17. Then the Papiſts may ſay, there is no <hi>Predeſtination</hi> of the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> they are onely <hi>fore-knowne,</hi> which is true <hi>in ſano ſenſu,</hi> but not in their ſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 8. Eightly, hence it followes, all men are diſpoſed and ordained of God, ſo as they may obtaine Eternall Life, if they will; their <hi>Predeſtination</hi> being like unto an <hi>Hypotheticall Propoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 9. Ninthly, hence follows <hi>falling from Grace,</hi> that the <hi>Seale</hi> of Gods <hi>Election</hi> is not <hi>ſure;</hi> that ſome, who were given to Chriſt, may be loſt: Or as if after our <hi>Regeneration,</hi> there were, as at our <hi>Creation, a poſſe mori,</hi> we might die from God; woe to man, if his condition were the ſame in the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> that it was in the <hi>firſt:</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118118:15"/> Indeed <hi>ſides, quae creditur,</hi> may be <hi>forſaken,</hi> but <hi>from,</hi> or <hi>a ſide, qua creditur,</hi> we <hi>cannot fall away.</hi> It is contrary to the ſixteenth <hi>Article,</hi> which is againſt a <hi>totall,</hi> and <hi>finall fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from Grace;</hi> for the Article ſpeakes of falling into <hi>ſinne</hi> after <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and <hi>riſing againe,</hi> by the ſame <hi>Grace:</hi> Now he that <hi>falleth finally,</hi> cannot <hi>riſe againe,</hi> and he that falleth totally from Grace, cannot riſe againe by the Grace he had received, becauſe he is ſuppoſed to have loſt all the Grace he received. <hi rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> all of them united, diſclaime the Doctrine of <hi>falling from Grace:</hi> Indeed the <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> required by the <hi>Law</hi> may be <hi>loſt,</hi> and it is of that, the Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. But the <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> promiſed by the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel cannot be loſt. Card. Bellarm.</hi> himſelfe ſpeakes truth ſometimes in this particular, touching the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of <hi>Saints;</hi> it is true (ſaith he) that the <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> or <hi>Elected</hi> are in no danger of <hi>loſing Eternall Life;</hi> and that the terrifying threats uſed by the Holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures are to this end, to ſtirre up the <hi>Elect</hi> to watchfulneſſe and diligence, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Juſtif. cap.</hi> 12. ſo that <hi>Motives</hi> they are to, and <hi>Meanes</hi> of <hi>Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> no <hi>Arguments</hi> at all, to prove the <hi>Saints Apoſtacy.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 10. Tenthly, hence <hi>Juſtification</hi> by <hi>God onely</hi> is utterly overthrowne, even in the Nature of it, which ſignifies <hi>juſtum facere,</hi> to make juſt, not <hi>invenire,</hi> to finde us juſt: for <hi>Juſtification</hi> is the Action of God without us. <hi rend="margQuotes">To the Faithfull there belongeth a <hi>two fold Righteouſnes;</hi> the one of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> the other of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> the former is the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> becauſe it is the Righteouſneſſe of him that is God, and is imputed onely to the <hi>Believer:</hi> The latter is <hi>ours,</hi> becauſe inherent in us, though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118118:16"/> from God, as all our good things are; of this ſecond there is no queſtion, and the firſt being <hi>ab extra</hi> cannot be from our fore-ſeene Faith or Workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 11. Eleventhly, hence it followes, that God cannot tell who are his, till they <hi>perſevere to the end;</hi> and therefore <hi>Arminius</hi> was forced to make the Object of Gods Decree, onely <hi>qui vixerunt: quoties fideles ſtatuimus objectum Electionis, toties nos fidem, &amp; perſeverantiam in fide conjungimus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grevinchovius:</hi> Our Regiſter Bookes muſt firſt be given in, ſuch a man dyed ſuch a day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his name can be written in the Regiſter Booke of God; contrary to <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 15. where <hi>Paul</hi> is called a <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Veſſell,</hi> even whilſt he was a <hi>Perſecutor,</hi> and was going to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> with that intent; and contrary to <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 48. where in the firſt inſtance of their Converſion, it is ſayd, <hi>As many as were ordained to eternall life did believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſurd.</hi> 12. Laſtly, <hi>Univerſall Grace,</hi> or <hi>Univerſall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> was the opinion of that wicked Heretick, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> condemned in a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> held at <hi>Malta,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare 425. againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> at which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was preſent, and 214. <hi>Biſhops:</hi> and at a <hi>Counſell</hi> in <hi>Affrick,</hi> where all the Provinces came together, in the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> and <hi>Celeſtine</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> to condemne <hi>Pelagius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſper</hi> in an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> which hee writ to <hi>Auguſtine de Reliquiis Pelagianae Haereſeos,</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>Hane Pelagianorum definitionem, &amp; profeſſionemeſſe; Univerſis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus propitiationem, quae eſt in ſacramento ſanguinis Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, ſine exceptione eſſe propoſitam; pro Univerſo humano ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere mortuum eſſe Dominum noſtrum Jeſum Chriſtum, &amp; neminem prorſus a Redemptione ſanguin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ejus exceptum, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiamſi omnem hanc vitam alieniſſimam ab eo mente per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſeat:</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118118:16"/> that is, the <hi>Pelagians</hi> profeſſe that the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation into, or by the bloud of Chriſt, without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is common to all: that Chriſt died for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and none is excepted, although he be all his life time ignorant of Chriſt: <hi>Ad ſalutis donum omnes homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Univerſaliter vocari, ſive per Naturalem, ſive per Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem ſcriptam, ſive per Evangelicam praedicationem:</hi> All men Univerſally are called to ſalvation either by Nature, by the Law written, or by the preaching of the Goſpel, ſo <hi>Pelagius, Prospers Epiſt:</hi> to <hi>Auguſt. Com.</hi> 7. And <hi>Auguſt. contra Julian. Pelag. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. ſaith thus: <hi>Deus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne mundum Redemit? Ecce videmus homines in peccatis ſuis vivere, quomodo putabimus Redemptos, quos permanere videmus Captivos? redimuntur, ſed non liberantur; haec ſunt Sententiarum portenta veſtrarum, haec inopinata myſteria dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum novorum, haec Paradoxa Pelagianorum Haereticorum:</hi> That is, hath God Redeemed the whole world? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! we ſee men live ſtill in their ſinnes; how can we think them to be Redeemed, that continue ſtill Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive? they are Redeemed out of Priſon, and yet they are in Priſon; theſe are your monſtrous imaginations; theſe are your idle myſterious conceits; theſe are the Paradoxes of Pelagian Hereticks.</p>
            <p>If any man liſt to ſee theſe Opinions proved <hi>Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> let him read <hi>Perkins, Tom.</hi> 1. againſt <hi>Univerſall Grace,</hi> and his whole Tractate of <hi>Gods Free Grace,</hi> and <hi>Mans Free Will;</hi> Doctor <hi>Davenant,</hi> his whole Book ſet out after the Councell of <hi>Dort;</hi> Doctor <hi>White,</hi> his <hi>Way,</hi> and <hi>Defence of the Way;</hi> Doctor <hi>Twiſſe,</hi> Doctor <hi>Wille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Beza, Pet. Martyr,</hi> and all the <hi>Divines</hi> of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, that writ of this Subject: If any object, this, and that particular man among the Proteſtants
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118118:17"/> were of a contrary Opinion, I anſwer, ſo they might, and yet I may plead the Proteſtant Churches: from this generall Rule, there may be two or three Exceptions, or <hi>William Lilly</hi> is out, and ſo is the whole Word. And that theſe Opinions are plain Papiſtry, ſee <hi>Perkins, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pa.</hi> 98. he reckons up ſixteene Errors of the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> and they, and our <hi>Univerſaliſts</hi> agree in almoſt all of them. In Doctor <hi>Whites Way,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> the maine Controverſies betwixt him, and the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits are concerning <hi>Univerſall Redemption;</hi> whether <hi>God</hi> will have <hi>all men to be ſaved:</hi> falling away <hi>from Grace:</hi> certainty of <hi>Grace and ſalvation: foreſeene Faith</hi> and <hi>Works: Free-will;</hi> whether God have <hi>determined all men,</hi> good and evill, <hi>to certaine Ends;</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuites, Arminians,</hi> and our <hi>Univerſaliſts</hi> agree in all theſe Opinions. Sure none is ſo ignorant, but if he know any thing, he knows <hi>Univerſall Redemption</hi> was the very top of the <hi>Arminian Tenets</hi> at the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Dort:</hi> it is an Article of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians Faith,</hi> the cooperation of <hi>Mans Free will with Grace in the firſt Converſion;</hi> and the power it hath to hinder, <hi>and fruſtrate</hi> the worke of <hi>Regenerating</hi> Grace; totall and <hi>finall</hi> falling <hi>away</hi> from <hi>the Grace of Juſtification:</hi> theſe and the like were the Doctrines of <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> and they are the ſubject of every Sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our <hi>Univerſaliſts:</hi> all the Churches of Lower <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> made a complaint to King <hi>James</hi> againſt the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and yet ſuch Offenders finde a Sanctuary among our <hi>Univerſaliſts;</hi> Therefore I conclude thus:</p>
            <p>If <hi>Univerſall Redemption</hi> was the old Hereſie of the <hi>Pelagians;</hi> if it be reckoned up among the groſſeſt Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and agrees in all things with the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians;</hi> then it ought not to be defended, or Preached
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118118:17"/> by us <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> but <hi>Univerſall Redemption</hi> was the old Hereſie of the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lagians,</hi> is reputed among the <hi>greſſeſt</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and agrees in all things with <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians;</hi> therefore it ought not to bee defended or Preached by us <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> The like <hi>Argument</hi> I may uſe againſt all thoſe that defend <hi>Univerſall Election, Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Vocation, Foreſeene Faith, and Works, falling away from Grace, Free Will, &amp;c.</hi> All theſe are mong the groſſeſt Opinions of <hi>Pelagians, Papiſts, Arminians: Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe Opinions were truth, then no marvell, if men run ſo faſt, as we ſee they doe run; for what a brave thing is it, that God will have all men to bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their ſenſe? what a comfortable Doctrine, that <hi>Grace</hi> ſhall be <hi>offered to every one effectually,</hi> whether he be of the Church or not, at one time or other, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or howſoever he live? Chriſt died for all, and there will be an offerture of peace on Gods part, which is in mans power to accept, when he pleaſes. No wonder if men live, as they liſt, and doe as wee ſee they doe, this doore being opened to all impieties; for yet there is a time (ſay they) when <hi>Grace</hi> ſhall bee offered <hi>effectually</hi> to <hi>All.</hi> Let mee urge a few <hi>Arguments</hi> in <hi>forme,</hi> not ſo much againſt my Adverſaries, that can ſay nothing, but becauſe I know there are in other Places, that are able to ſay ſomething: And firſt againſt <hi>Univerſall Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> I reaſon thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. To whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> for them he was an <hi>Interceſſor;</hi> theſe two <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ought not to be disjoined; but <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not an <hi>Interceſſor</hi> for <hi>all</hi> and <hi>every one; I pray for them, I pray not for the World, John</hi> 17. 9. therefore it followes, hee <hi>Redeemed not all,</hi> and every one: they cannot bring one place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118118:18"/> to prove he <hi>prayed</hi> for <hi>all;</hi> and yet to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>all</hi> was far ſhort of <hi>powring</hi> forth his <hi>Bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2, If <hi>Chriſt died for all,</hi> and every one, then hee <hi>roſe againe, aſcended, and ſitteth at his Fathers right hand,</hi> for <hi>all,</hi> and every one; but ſure they are afraid to ſay the laſt, therefore they may be aſhamed to ſay the firſt: disjoyne theſe <hi>Offices</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, ſitting at the right hand of God;</hi> and they make <hi>Chriſt</hi> but halfe a Saviour; conjoyne them, and by their Opinion, it is impoſſible but <hi>all</hi> men muſt be <hi>ſaved,</hi> if Chriſt as he died, ſo he roſe againe, aſcended, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at his Fathers right hand for <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a <hi>Lambe ſlaine from the begining of the world:</hi> from thence I reaſon thus; if <hi>Chriſt died for all,</hi> and every one, then he <hi>died</hi> for <hi>Caine, Eſau, Pharaoh,</hi> wicked <hi>Jeroboam, Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> then rayling <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakey</hi> had his part in <hi>Chriſt, Julian</hi> the Apoſtata, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Judas,</hi> and all that were damned, yea, and Divells in Hell many thouſand yeares before hee ſuffered death: but ſure Chriſtians cannot ſay this: I wonder therfore any Chriſtian can ſay that: did hee actually ſhed his bloud in the laſt Age of the World, for them that were damned in Hell in the firſt Age of the World? Whether is this more ridiculous, or impious?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If <hi>Chriſt died,</hi> obteyned <hi>Remiſſion of ſinnes,</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation</hi> with <hi>God</hi> for <hi>all,</hi> then none <hi>are borne</hi> the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>wrath</hi> by <hi>nature, or are obnoxious to death and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for Originall ſinne; all are borne</hi> in the ſtate of <hi>Grace:</hi> but the Scripture ſaith, <hi>we are by nature the ſonnes of wrath;</hi> and they dare not ſay, that we are <hi>borne</hi> in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Grace;</hi> then how can they ſay, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Remiſſion of ſins</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation</hi> with God for <hi>all?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118118:18"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. If <hi>Chriſt redeemed all,</hi> and every particular man, then <hi>God wills the ſalvation of all,</hi> &amp; of every particular man; it's true, they affirme both of theſe, and I prove them both falſe on this manner: for either God wills not, or he wills the ſalvation of every particular man; if God will not the ſalvation of every particular man, it is that which we ſay, the Scriptures, and the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches with us: if he will and cannot, or will and doth not, (which is all one) as the <hi>Papiſts, Pelagians, Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Univerſaliſts</hi> ſay, then how is God Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, if he cannot doe what he wills; or will he once ſave all, and will he not-afterward? Is God mutable as man? No ſure; his name is, <hi>I am;</hi> he is the <hi>ſame yeſterday and to day; hee is in one minde,</hi> Job 23. 13. <hi>With God is no variableneſſe, nor ſhadow of change,</hi> Ja. 1. 17. God wills a Change, but he changeth not; there may be <hi>mutatio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> not <hi>deereti: Nineveh</hi> was changed, but there was no change in God. <hi>Incomplete,</hi> and <hi>compleat, antecedent,</hi> and <hi>conſequent wills</hi> are fictions of our Adverſaries, and are the Attributes of ſome other God: our God is one, &amp; ſo is the <hi>will</hi> of our God; <hi>He but willed, and it was ſo,</hi> Gen. 1. 6. 9. <hi>Dixit &amp; factum eſt, willing,</hi> and <hi>Doing</hi> are all one with God: <hi>in him, for him, by him, and through him alone are all things,</hi> Rom. 12. 36. That <hi>Idea Divina</hi> is both the Being, and the well Being of every thing in Heaven, or Earth: <hi>he worketh all things,</hi> upon no Condition, after no Example; <hi>but after the counſell of his owne will,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 5. He wills not therefore (it is not ſo, becauſe hee will not have it ſo) that every particular man ſhould be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. If <hi>Chriſt layd downe his life for his ſheepe;</hi> was delivered to Death for his Church and Children; <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> together <hi>Pilios Dei disperſos,</hi> the Sonnes of God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118118:19"/> in what place ſoever; died, and gave himſelfe to Redeeme a peculiar People, <hi>prayed not for all, &amp;c.</hi> Then <hi>he did not Redeeme everyone, Fideles,</hi> and <hi>Infideles; all</hi> are <hi>not Sheep, his Church, his Children, his People,</hi> nay, <hi>his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People,</hi> as it appeares, John 10. 27. 28. John 17. 9. and almoſt the whole Chapter, Tit. 2. 14. Acts 20. 28. Epheſ. 5. 25. John 1. 12. Pſal. 33. 12. <hi>ſed verum prius, ergo poſterius,</hi> the firſt is true, therefore the laſt. I know they diſtinguiſh 'twixt <hi>Impetration,</hi> which, they ſay, was for <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>reall fruition,</hi> which, they ſay, is but for a <hi>few;</hi> Chriſts prayers, they feigne, are meant of the firſt, not of the laſt; but it is falſe; for theſe prayers were fulfilled, <hi>eo ipſo momento, quo Chriſtus ponebat ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam,</hi> at that inſtant when Chriſt laid downe his life, though the actuall fruition followed after: the prayers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> had been to ſmall purpoſe, had they not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ned both to the firſt, and laſt; there is not one place of Scripture, where <hi>Impetration</hi> is named without reſpect to <hi>Application;</hi> it muſt needs follow therefore, that <hi>Chriſt died</hi> not for <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. For whom <hi>Chriſt died,</hi> he <hi>ſo died,</hi> that <hi>he tooke their death and the punniſhment</hi> they <hi>deſerved</hi> upon <hi>himſelfe:</hi> ſo the Phraſe of dying for any is to be underſtood, as it is plaine, 2. Sam. 18. 33. Rom. 9. 3. but they dare not ſay, that Chriſt <hi>took</hi> the Death and Puniſhment, which all deſerved upon himſelfe, it is againſt John 3. 36. Mat, 7. 23. therefore he died not for All. How to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this Argument (which they are never able) they make themſelves <hi>Socinians,</hi> as in many things they make themſelves <hi>Maſſilians,</hi> they will hardly put mee to prove.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 8. All <hi>thoſe,</hi> for <hi>whom Chriſt died,</hi> may ſay, <hi>who can</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118118:19"/> 
               <hi>condemne us? Chriſt died for us; who ſhall ſeperate us from the love of Chriſt?</hi> Rom. 8. 34. 35. but all cannot ſay ſo, for there are infinites condemned, and therefore Chriſt died not for All.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 9. <hi>Are all thoſe, whom Univerſaliſts ſay have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this Grace of Redemption, Regenerate? or are they not Regenerate?</hi> if they be <hi>Regenerate,</hi> then <hi>all men</hi> are <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate;</hi> if not, then have all men power to believe, and to <hi>attaine</hi> ſalvation, if they will, <hi>whileſt they</hi> remaine unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate: they <hi>will not</hi> ſay the firſt, and <hi>Pelagius</hi> could ſay no more then the laſt.</p>
            <p>I might double this number of Arguments againſt <hi>Univerſall Redemption,</hi> but that may bee done when my Adverſaries undertake to anſwer theſe; which they (that is the <hi>Thomſoniſts)</hi> will never attempt. Yet let me alledge the words of Mr. <hi>Perkins, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 302. where he ſaith thus; <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Univerſall Grace appertaining to all, and every man, may ſitly be termed the Schoole of Univerſall Atheiſme,</hi> for it pulls downe the Pale of the Church, and laies it waſte, like to a common Field; it breeds a careleſneſſe, in the uſe of the means of Grace, the Word, and Sacraments, when as men ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that <hi>Grace ſhall be offered to every one effectually, whether he be of the Church or not, at one time or other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, or howſoever he live, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Now whether were the Smith, the Miller, the Thatcher, the Thraſher, or he that ſent and ſet them on, more ignorant, or impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, to charge me, and all the Reformed Churches with me, of high Treaſon againſt the Crowne Royalty, Love, Goodneſſe, Soverainty of the Son of God, for the words, which, the truth is, I tooke out of Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in the place aforeſaid; they might have had more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118118:20"/> to that worthy Mans memory, though they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not me. It may be at that grand meeting, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, and do me ſome miſchiefe (they know where, and when,) they all laid their little wits together to deviſe and draw the Charge; but the Smith that read it, writ it ſure, it was ſo like him, Children challenge their Parents, <hi>like Lips, like Lettice,</hi> the Matter and the Letter ſtunke much what alike. Thus fearfully they fall, whom God forſakes; they run out of one Extreame over the <hi>Medium</hi> into another Extreame, and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle cals it, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 2. quite out of their wits; High <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt <hi>the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (ſo they call their <hi>Vniverſall Redemption, Free will, &amp;c.) charged upon, or againſt all the Reformed Churches at once by ſuch men of ignorance: Father forgive them, they knew not what they did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let me uſe a few Arguments againſt their ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Election.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If <hi>perſeverance</hi> bee a <hi>condition</hi> required in the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> as they ſay, then there are <hi>none Elect</hi> til the <hi>End of this life:</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> is called an <hi>Elect Veſſell,</hi> even whileſt he was a <hi>Perſecutor,</hi> Act. 9. 15. And S. <hi>John</hi> wrot his <hi>ſecond Epiſtle, to the elect Lady,</hi> (yet alive) and <hi>her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> 1. John 2. 1. Therefore <hi>Perſeverance</hi> can bee <hi>no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> required in the <hi>Objection of Election;</hi> the Antecedent is confeſſed, for <hi>perſeverance</hi> is a part of their <hi>Theſis,</hi> as I ſhewed out of <hi>Ameſius de Electione, pa.</hi> 1. neither do they deny it; then the Conſequence cannot be denied; how can it bee knowne who will <hi>perſevere to the end,</hi> whileſt they are yet <hi>alive?</hi> The Minor is true, for they are the words of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> and S. <hi>John, ut ſuprà;</hi> and I could prove it out of a hundred places; therefore the Concluſion cannot be falſe, <hi>Perſeverance can be no condition in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118118:20"/> 
               <hi>of Election.</hi> They, even all of them, <hi>Univerſaliſts, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Arminians,</hi> defend <hi>falling away from Grace,</hi> and they prove it, <hi>de facto,</hi> by a fearfull Argument; for they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have <hi>faln from the Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. They who <hi>were given to Chriſt, antecedenter ad Fidem,</hi> that <hi>they might be Faithfull,</hi> they were <hi>Elect antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter ad Fidem,</hi> that <hi>they might have Faith and Perſeveranee,</hi> not <hi>becauſe</hi> they were <hi>ſuch;</hi> but <hi>ſome are given to Chriſt</hi> that they might have <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance;</hi> therefore they were <hi>elect,</hi> that <hi>they might be Faithfull,</hi> not for <hi>their Faith:</hi> the Major none can deny, and the Minor may be proved out of Epheſ. 1. 4. <hi>Hee hath choſen us before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould bee holy, and without blame before him, not becauſe we were holy:</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith the ſame, Epheſ. 2. 10. <hi>Faith is the fruit, not the tree; the Effect, not the Cauſe of Election:</hi> we are <hi>elected to faith, not for faith; antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter ad fidem,</hi> as I ſaid, not <hi>propter fidem;</hi> there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cauſe of our <hi>Election,</hi> but only the <hi>Will of God.</hi> Nay more, the <hi>mediation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not the Cauſe of Gods Decree, but Gods Decree, <hi>è contra,</hi> is the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſts mediation; he Predeſtinated us unto the Adoption of Children, by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the good pleaſure of his owne will,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 5. The Jewes were rejected for their unbeliefe; the Gentiles were not elected for their Faith, but <hi>they ſtood by Faith,</hi> Rom. 11. 20. We never read, that any People, or particular Nation was elected for their <hi>Faith;</hi> the contrary we often read, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 7. 8. <hi>&amp; Ezek.</hi> 16. Firſt, <hi>the Lord ſaith, this is my People, before the People can ſay, the Lord is our God,</hi> Zach. 13. 9. <hi>Vera Electio non inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, ſed facit fideles,</hi> true Election finds us not, but makes us faithfull; <hi>Qui enim de mundo mundum eligi fecit, quod eligeret, non invenit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtin in Joh.</hi> 15. God choſe a World out of the World, for nothing that was in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118118:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> the World. Indeed <hi>Arminius</hi> ſtands to it ſtoutly, that Faith in Gods Decree of Election doth, in order, goe before, not follow Election: But yet that old Axiome is, and will be truth, when Hereſies and Hereticks are dead, &amp; with the Devill, their Father; <hi>Deus in negotio Predeſtinationis non egreditur extràſe,</hi> God in <hi>Predeſtination</hi> goes not out of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. The Scriptures teach us, that <hi>on ſome God will ſhew Mercy, on others his Juſtice,</hi> Exod. 33. 19. Rom. 9. 22. 23. <hi>of his owne Free Will,</hi> or <hi>good pleaſure;</hi> which proves that <hi>Election</hi> is neither <hi>for Faith,</hi> nor <hi>of all: Of the ſame Clay the Potter maketh both the Veſſels that ſerve for cleane uſes; and likewiſe alſo ſuch as ſerve to the contrary;</hi> but what is the uſe of either ſort, the <hi>Potter</hi> himſelfe is the <hi>Judge,</hi> Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome 15. 7. <hi>O houſe of Iſrael, can not I doe with you, as the Potter,</hi> ſaith the Lord? <hi>Behold as the clay is in the Potters hand, ſo are ye in mine, O houſe of Iſrael,</hi> Jer. 18. 6. And if any man will ſtrive againſt God, for doing with us as he pleaſeth, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> pronounceth a woe againſt ſuch an one; <hi>Woe unto him that ſtriveth with his Maker:</hi> Let the <hi>potſherds ſtrive with the potſherds of the earth: ſhall the Clay ſay to him that faſhioneth it, what makeſt thou? Woe unto him that ſaith to his Father, what begetteſt thou? &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 45. 9. 10. God hath got the upper ground, doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. Chriſt ſaith hee had ſheep among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; <hi>Other ſheep I have that are not of this fold,</hi> John 10. 16 Therefore <hi>God had much people among them, that had not heard of him:</hi> now this cannot be <hi>by Election,</hi> or in <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,</hi> and Eternall Counſell of God; therefore there is a ſingular <hi>Election, even of ſuch as never had Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Our Adverſaries might remember, Chriſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118118:21"/> ſayth, <hi>But many are called, and fewer choſen,</hi> Matt. 20. 16. &amp; 22. 14. From which words it followes, there is <hi>neither an univerſall Vocation, nor an univerſall Election:</hi> but I tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched theſe things before, and ſhall heereafter, when I come to prove <hi>Gods abſolute Decree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Univerſall Vocation</hi> is of the ſame ſtampe with their <hi>Univerſall Election,</hi> as counterfet coyne, I proved it before, and I may adde further. This Opinion neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily implies, that God gives <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>means ſufficient</hi> for <hi>ſalvation to all men;</hi> and ſuppoſes that there is no mortall man, old, or yong, Chriſtian, or Pagan, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World, unto the end thereof, but God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales to him the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>ſalvation;</hi> and, at leaſt, in ſome inſtant of his life, he ſets him in ſuch a <hi>ſtate,</hi> that he may <hi>enjoy the means if he will, and be ſaved:</hi> the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is thus proved, becauſe, if God will onely ſave ſuch as uſe the <hi>means of ſalvation well,</hi> and <hi>damn</hi> ſuch as uſe them <hi>ill,</hi> and that conſequently, <hi>becauſe they uſe them well or ill;</hi> then he muſt in juſtice <hi>reveale and exhibit theſe means unto them,</hi> becauſe no man by himſelfe can reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them; and hee muſt reveale and exhibite them to man, when he is in ſuch a ſtate, that he hath the uſe of his <hi>Free Will;</hi> as a King that wills the ſafety of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, on condition that they keep his Lawes, is bound to publiſh and make his Lawes known unto them; elſe if he execute any of them, it muſt be upon a new point, and not upon their not keeping his Lawes; ſo alſo it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> that <hi>God ſhould reprobate any,</hi> for the <hi>ill uſe of his grace,</hi> and <hi>contempt of the means of ſalvation, that never had thoſe meanes,</hi> nor ever <hi>heard</hi> of his <hi>grace;</hi> as many milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of people in all Ages have beene, and now are. The firſt ſort whereof are <hi>Infants,</hi> that either die <hi>in the womb,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118118:22"/> or <hi>unbaptized,</hi> or reach not to years <hi>of diſcretion,</hi> and the <hi>uſe</hi> of <hi>reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Free Will:</hi> now <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> is of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon in Infants, then in Old folke, but upon the ſame grounds, and in the ſame maner, that God wills the ſalvation of the one, he wills the ſalvation of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then let the <hi>Univerſaliſt</hi> tell me, <hi>how the means of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is applied to Infants,</hi> or how they <hi>can make uſe of the means?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort, that never had, or heard of the <hi>means</hi> of ſalvation, are <hi>Idiots,</hi> ſuch as are born Naturalls, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe of Reaſon; of whom the ſame may be ſayd, that is of Infants, that for want of Reaſon, and <hi>the uſe of Free Will, they cannot be ſaid to have ſufficient means:</hi> for to the ſufficiency of the meanes muſt concurre not only the perfection of the helpe revealed, but alſo the ability of the Subject, to whom the ſayd helpe is offered; if God have left his Word to lead a man, and yet with-holds Reaſon and faculty from him, that hee cannot hear, nor uſe it, it cannot bee conceived, how hee may bee ſayd to have left ſufficient meanes to that man.</p>
            <p>The third ſort, that never had the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> are <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> that never heard of God, or Chriſt, or the Goſpel, theſe alſo cannot be ſayd to have <hi>ſufficient means of ſalvation;</hi> becauſe the <hi>revelation of Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel is the means,</hi> and they <hi>never</hi> had it: if it bee objected, that the Heathen may have certaine inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which may guide them firſt to Grace, and then to Glory; then I demand, firſt touching theſe inſpirations, that are ſayd to bee thus offered, and ſtirred up in the Gentiles, are they ſuper-naturall, or naturall? if ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, by what meanes are they wrought? for the Word of God they have not, and Gods <hi>Spirit</hi> doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118118:22"/> ſufficiently inſpire, when it doth not ſufficiently reveale it ſelfe to be his Spirit; are they naturall, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing only from a naturall knowledge? then I demand againe, whether they bee able to bring him, that hath them to <hi>Juſtifying Grace?</hi> if they be not able, they are inſufficient; if they ſay they be able, then this is <hi>Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> that a man by naturall ſtrength may obtaine the Grace of God.</p>
            <p>Two prodigious Opinions have I read touching this poynt; <hi>[In Whites Way, pag.</hi> 280.] one of the Papiſts, or ſome of them, who ſay, that the very Gentiles knew God, and did many things wherein was no ſinne, and this was ſufficient to ſave them.</p>
            <p>The other of that man of ignorance, who wrote the Charge of high Treaſon againſt all, that deny <hi>Univerſall Redemption;</hi> there hee ſaith, (but God helpe him, hee knowes not what he ſaith) that man hath yet liberty and power to eſcape Condemnation, and can doe that which God Commands. Theſe Opinions are fitter for <hi>Pelagians,</hi> who ſay, <hi>Gratia ſignificat naturam ratione, &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate praeditam,</hi> that Grace is Nature indued with <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Free Will;</hi> and that <hi>per Opera Naturae homo prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur auxilium gratiae,</hi> a man may open the window to let Grace come in, as (beſides <hi>Pelagians)</hi> moſt of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> ſay, but they become not us, who profeſſe our ſelves Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Yet further, to prove that <hi>Infants, Idiots, Infidels ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had the meanes of Grace,</hi> I may ſay thus; that the <hi>word of Reconciliation was not preached to all; Reconciliation is by faith, and faith by the word,</hi> Ro. 10. 14. Which Word was not, nay is not yet preached to all: was there not a <hi>Partition wall till it was broken downe? Did not Chriſt charge</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118118:23"/> 
               <hi>his Diſciples, not to goe into the way of the Gentiles? nor into the Cities of the Samaritans?</hi> Mat. 10. 5. 6. Look into that Parable of the Woman of Canaan, if the <hi>Word of God</hi> was not the <hi>Childrens bread,</hi> Mat. 15. 24. 26. All the blind Americans, many of the barbarous Affricans, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadge Canibals, beſides the Chinoys, ſo quick-ſighted in other things, yet had not heard of a Saviour, till ſome few hundred years ſince: nay more, our Brethren, if they pleaſe to prove <hi>Univerſall Vocation,</hi> may bee yet, almoſt the firſt to Preach the word of God to a great part of <hi>Finmark,</hi> the <hi>Scricfinians, Lappians,</hi> and ſome Northerne Iſles within the <hi>Artick Circle,</hi> among us <hi>Europeans;</hi> then how can they dreame of <hi>Univerſall Vocation?</hi> Now our Queſtion is not, <hi>If grace be free,</hi> but whether <hi>this Free grace bee effectually and freely offered to all?</hi> Yea, but the Black-ſmith, in that ugly thing he brought, as blacke as himſelfe, tells us of the Spirit; but it was writ by a foul ſpirit: well, yet there were 12. Places of Scripture, to prove <hi>Univerſall Redemption,</hi> I think ſet downe by ſome ſimple Brother, ſure not by Mr. <hi>T.</hi> for hee applied not one place, but ſaid, they were plaine Places, and ſo left it ſimply to beleeve: now to theſe I need not anſwer, for they were barely named, and nothing concluded, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Syllogiſme nor ſence, but left ſimply as the Letter ſayd: yet in anſwer to them, and the like places, I ſay thus:</p>
            <p>There are ſeverall interpretations of ſuch places as ſay, <hi>God</hi> will have <hi>all</hi> to bee <hi>ſaved;</hi> the chiefe whereof are theſe foure, that follow: <hi rend="margQuotes">1. <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth,</hi> in that he makes us to wiſh, and deſire this our ſelves, by ſtirring us up to ſeeke and pray for ſalvation, becauſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118118:23"/> the Will that God workes in us is ſaid to bee Gods Will:</hi> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">2. Where the Scriptures ſay, God will have <hi>all</hi> to be <hi>ſaved;</hi> by the word, <hi>all,</hi> ſuch only are meant who are ſaved, by reſtraining the Univerſall ſigne to the <hi>Elect</hi> alone; that is, <hi>all who are ſaved, are all ſaved only by vertue of the Will of God;</hi> as a Schoole-Maſter may be ſaid to teach all the children in a Towne, when hee only teaches all that are taught:</hi> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">3. God by the <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of his <hi>Will</hi> revealed in his Word, would <hi>all men</hi> to bee <hi>ſaved,</hi> in as much, as hee <hi>offers</hi> to <hi>all</hi> men, either the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> or ſome other <hi>ſigne,</hi> whereby hee invites them to <hi>ſalvation;</hi> and this Expoſition denies, that there is any <hi>Will of good pleaſure,</hi> or abſolute <hi>Will</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> referred and determined to the <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> but onely to the <hi>Means</hi> propounded, which of themſelves are <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and able to lead men to <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> thereby he carries himſelfe as one that hath a purpoſe to ſave <hi>all:</hi> They call this <hi>Will of God, Voluntas Signi;</hi> not <hi>Beneplaciti;</hi> the Will of the Signe, but not his abſolute Will, which <hi>firſt</hi> may <hi>not be fulfilled,</hi> and yet the <hi>laſt;</hi> his <hi>abſolute Will</hi> is <hi>alwayes fulfilled:</hi>
               </hi> 4. God would have <hi>all</hi> to be <hi>ſaved,</hi> that is, <hi>he ſaveth ſome in all Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> not <hi>ſingula generum,</hi> but <hi>genera ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum,</hi> of all ſorts ſome, not every ſingular perſon of all ſorts, whether they be rich or poore, old or young, Jewes, Greekes, Barbarians, God ſaves ſome of every Condition: ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſayd to have <hi>Redeemed</hi> ſome <hi>out of every Kindred, and Tongue, and People, and Nation,</hi> Rev. 5. 9. to have <hi>healed every Diſeaſe,</hi> that is, <hi>every kinde of Diſeaſe</hi> Mat. 4. 23.</p>
            <p>This, and the ſecond <hi>diſtinction</hi> I thinke the beſt to be applyed to ſuch places of Scripture, where it is ſaid,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118118:24"/> 
               <hi>God will have all to be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, I ſay, that by the word, <hi>all,</hi> wee muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>all</hi> that <hi>believe; by him all that believe are juſtified,</hi> Acts 13. 39. <hi>all that are weary and heavy laden,</hi> Mat. 11. 28. <hi>He gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh,</hi> John. 3. 16. the <hi>Scripture hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all under ſin,</hi> that the <hi>Promiſe</hi> by the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, ſhould be given to them that believe,</hi> Gal. 3. 22. I might inferre, but <hi>all, and every one believes not;</hi> therefore <hi>Chriſt died not for All,</hi> and <hi>every one.</hi> It is apparent, that the word, <hi>All,</hi> is oftentimes uſed for <hi>Many;</hi> as Rom. 5. 18. 19. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Manuell to <hi>Laur: cap:</hi> 103. ſaith thus: <q rend="margQuotes">God would have <hi>all</hi> to bee <hi>ſaved;</hi> not becauſe there was no man which he would have damned; who therefore would not do miracles among them, which would (ſo he ſaith) have repented, if he had done mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; but by <hi>all men,</hi> we muſt underſtand, <hi>all ſorts of men,</hi> howſoever diſtinguiſhed, whether Kings, private perſons, &amp;c.</q> Theſe two, <hi>to be willing to ſave a man; and that he ſhould come to the ſaving knowledge of the Truth,</hi> are inſeperably united together, 1. Tim. 2. 4. but the ſecond, we ſee, doth not agree to all, and every ſingular perſon; therefore the firſt cannot.</p>
            <p>But here a queſtion may bee asked; did God then appoint <hi>all</hi> to bee <hi>ſaved,</hi> upon this Condition, <hi>if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?</hi> I anſwer, that it is abſurd to affirme this; for firſt, by that <hi>meanes</hi> the <hi>Decree</hi> of God ſhould depend upon the <hi>Will</hi> of man, whereas, on the contrary, Gods <hi>Decree</hi> doth limit and order all inferior <hi>Cauſes:</hi> ſecondly, it quite taketh away the certainty of <hi>Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,</hi> becauſe a Conditionall Propoſition doth ſet down nothing as being, or it doth not certainly affirme any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118118:24"/> thing; and wee are elected to Faith; not for Faith, I told you before.</p>
            <p>They object againe, (it is their uſuall Argument) <hi rend="margQuotes">If <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne <hi>deſtroyed all,</hi> and <hi>Chriſts merit</hi> doth not <hi>ſave all;</hi>
               </hi> then is <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne more forcible to <hi>condemne,</hi> then <hi>Chriſts</hi> mercy is to <hi>ſave:</hi> To this I anſwer, <hi rend="margQuotes">we muſt value the <hi>mercy</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the <hi>efficacy,</hi> and <hi>dignity</hi> of it; for it was a more eaſie thing to <hi>deſtroy all by ſin,</hi> then by <hi>Grace</hi> to <hi>ſave but one:</hi> man, being but meere man, could deſtroy <hi>all;</hi> but to <hi>ſave</hi> even <hi>one,</hi> none could do it, but ſuch an one, as was both God and Man; <hi>one man damned all,</hi> or brought them into the ſtate of damnation; <hi>but all men cannot ſave one.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they object, that God is cruel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith Mr. <hi>T.</hi> I wonder, how he did to write the word; hee goes further, <hi>God</hi> is an <hi>Abaddon,</hi> (for he uſeth as ill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage againſt God Almighty, as againſt me) if he <hi>ordain any,</hi> or the <hi>moſt of men to damnation.</hi> To this I anſwer, that he chargeth me, and the Reformed Churches falſly; We ſay, <hi>ſinne damnes; God damnes not, but for ſinne:</hi> and yet I know our <hi>Thomſoniſts</hi> are not able to anſwer that of <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 9. 21. where he ſayth, <hi>the Potter makes of, the ſame clay ſome veſſels to diſhonour:</hi> nor to that, Prov. 16. 4. <hi>The Lord made even the wicked for the day of evill:</hi> nor to that of Jude 4. <hi>Tbere are certaine men crept in unawares, who were before of old Ordained unto this Condemnation:</hi> Let them looke into Exo. 33. 19. Jer. 18. 6. Iſa. 45. 9. 10. if God may not take leave to do what he liſt.</p>
            <p>This indeed we do ſay, that <hi>God in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternall Decree did paſſe by ſome, with a purpoſe not to ſhew mercy on ſuch, which purpoſe cauſeth no neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of damnation, but by the ſinne of man comming betweene.</hi> Secondly, We ſay, <hi>God could</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118118:25"/> 
               <hi>have Decreed, that even All men ſhould have been utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and yet he ſhould have been neither cruell nor unjuſt:</hi> he adjudged all and every one of thoſe foule and wicked ſpirits which fell from him to eternall torments, was he cruell in that? he Decreed that men ſhould live by the ſlaughter of Beaſts, is he cruell in that? God is no more bounden unto man, then unto bruit Beaſts.</p>
            <p>But they object, that Chriſt tooke upon him <hi>the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man,</hi> therefore he redeemed <hi>the nature of man,</hi> and ſo by <hi>conſequence every man</hi> that pertakes of <hi>humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> To this I anſwer, that it followeth not, except we ſay, that Chriſt <hi>Redeemed himſelfe,</hi> he alſo did <hi>partake of humane nature;</hi> but they dare not ſay, that Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed himſelfe: every woman doth partake the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of every man, yet is not every man each womans husband, but hers alone, to whom he is joyned in Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; and <hi>Chriſt alſo tooke upon him mans nature,</hi> common to all <hi>Adams</hi> Poſterity, <hi>yet is he the husband of his Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, be gave himſelfe for it,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 25. <hi>that he might ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and cleanſe it,</hi> v. 26. <hi>that he might preſent it a glorious Church,</hi> v. 27. and ſo <hi>the Church became fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone,</hi> v. 30. Therefore <hi>the Church alone can juſtly challenge a title in, and to the death of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they object againe, that in many Places Chriſt is ſayd <hi>to redeeme the World,</hi> as 1. John. 2. 2. Mr. <hi>T.</hi> chargeth with this Argument almoſt as violently, as the Duke of <hi>Byron</hi> did his Enemies, of whom they report, that the bloud burſt out of his lips, at every Charge. For De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our ſelves therefore, wee ſay thus; This word, <hi>World,</hi> ſignifies, 1. <hi>The frame of Heaven and Earth.</hi> 2. <hi>All, both good and bad together.</hi> 3. <hi>The company of Unbeleevers and haters of Chriſt.</hi> 4. <hi>The congregation of the Elect diſperſed over</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118118:25"/> 
               <hi>the face of the whole World, and to be gathered out of the World:</hi> In this fourth ſignification wee muſt underſtand that Place of <hi>John,</hi> and the like places: thus the <hi>Church</hi> is oft called by the name of the <hi>World,</hi> as 2. Cor. 5. 19. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World;</hi> that <hi>World,</hi> it followes, <hi>to whom their ſinnes are not imputed.</hi> In <hi>John</hi> 6. 3. <hi>Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the bread of life, that came downe from heaven, and gave life to the World:</hi> there is both <hi>Impetration,</hi> and <hi>Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> he gave ſpirituall life, which can be meant of none, but the <hi>Elect</hi> alone, who are <hi>there called the World:</hi> the ſame St. <hi>John</hi> expounds himſelfe, what he meant by the <hi>World,</hi> John 10. 27. 28. <hi>My Sheepe heare my voyce, and I give them eternall life; they onely therefore are that enlivened World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know, they object againſt us that of <hi>Paul; God is the Saviour of all men,</hi> eſpecially, <hi>of them that believe,</hi> 1. Tim. 4. 10. But the <hi>proper meaning</hi> of that place <hi>is,</hi> God <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, provides</hi> for, and is <hi>good to all,</hi> eſpecially <hi>to them that believe;</hi> he makes his Sun to ſhine upon all, and ſends them Raine and Showres: <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore they compare God to a Maſter of a Family, who is good to all his ſervants, yea, to his Cattle; the very Hogs, and Dogs he keepes, but to his Wife and Children he is very good. <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates the Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in that place, not <hi>Salvator,</hi> but <hi>Conſervator;</hi> and <hi>Aretius</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the ſame Verſe ſaith, <hi>Deus omnium, maximè Fidelium, Benefactor;</hi> God is a Benefactor of, to <hi>all,</hi> but eſpecially to the <hi>Elect:</hi>
               </hi> The moſt and beſt Interpreters make this the meaning of the words: <q rend="margQuotes">Earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings he poures out to every one; but we no where read, that God, <hi>Voluntate beneplaciti,</hi> by his abſolute Will, <hi>would</hi> have every <hi>particular</hi> man <hi>to be ſaved.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118118:26"/>
            <p> That place, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 1. Where <hi>Reprobates</hi> are ſayd to be <hi>redeemed by Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>meant</hi> of ſuch as <hi>live</hi> in the <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> who are ſayd to be <hi>redeemed,</hi> both in their <hi>owne Judgements,</hi> and in the <hi>Churches Judgement</hi> of <hi>Charity;</hi> and thus the <hi>Miniſters</hi> may, and doe apply <hi>Chriſts death</hi> and <hi>Redemption</hi> to <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many Objections of leſſer Conſequence, but why ſhould I teach my Adverſaries, who are as wilfull, as they would be wicked? the greateſt comfort I have, is, that if I cannot convert them (which I hope) yet a veſſell can hold no more, then it is able to contain. I conclude this Poynt therefore with that of <hi>Aquinas: Chriſts merit, according to the ſufficiency thereof, carrieth it ſelf indifferently to all, but not according to the Efficacy;</hi> which comes to paſſe, partly by Gods Election, through which the effect of Chriſts merits is mercifully beſtowed on ſome, and partly by the juſt Judgements of Gods, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his Grace from other ſome.</p>
            <p>Now to fortifie, &amp; rivet all this Building by yet more impregnable Reaſons; I will prove it no cruelty in God, to doe with his Creature what he pleaſeth; that <hi>God</hi> may <hi>elect,</hi> or <hi>reject whom he liſt;</hi> and that there is <hi>no other cauſe of Gods Decree of Election, but his owne Will:</hi> The fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our Univerſaliſts I will confute by theſe <hi>Theſes</hi> following.</p>
            <p>I aſſert therefore; That <hi>Predeſtination is an eternall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, in time cauſing effectuall Grace, in all thoſe whom he hath choſen, and by this effectuall Grace bringing them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly to Glory: Now this Election, or Dilection of ſome, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a paſſing by of others, and a leaving them to their owne ſelves; the cauſe of both is nothing elſe, but the Will of God: The Parts of this Decree are two, Election, and Reprobation;</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118118:26"/> 
               <hi>the firſt, Gods abſolute Decree of preparing that Grace for ſome, which will preſerve them; the ſecond, Gods abſolute Decree of not preparing for others that Grace, which would preſerve them. Now theſe Decrees are not founded upon any different fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene Acts of men, but upon the alone Will of God, which is the moſt abſolute, ſupreame, and ſoveraigne Cauſe of all things that are; having nothing either above it ſelfe, or out of it ſelfe, to be any impulſive Cauſe, to move, or incline it: Indeed, mens Wils are moved, and diſpoſed by externall Cauſes out of themſelves, becauſe they are to be ruled by Equity, and Reaſon; and a mans bare Will, without a Reaſon, is nothing; but Gods Will is not ruled by another Will, or Rule of Reaſon or Juſtice; but it ſelfe is an abſolute Rule both of Juſtice, and Reaſon.</hi> A thing is not firſt of all reaſonable and juſt, and afterward willed by God; but it is firſt of all willed by God, and thereupon it becomes reaſonable and juſt; <hi>Volitiones purè conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales ſunt alienae a ſapientia divina, Decrees</hi> meerly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall agree not with the perfection of the Divine Nature; ſuch <hi>Volitions,</hi> or <hi>Decrees</hi> are for us, who have neither Knowledge, whether the condition will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, nor power to worke the condition, upon which the future Act of our Will was ſuſpended: But in God who knoweth what every man will, or will not do, and hath power to make men do the good he will, <hi>theſe Conditionall Decrees are not purely, but mixtly Conditionall:</hi> that is, <hi>grounded on ſome abſolute revealed Decree of God, to the performance whereof he hath tied himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we ought to obſerve, that <hi>Reprobation,</hi> and <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> differ exceedingly much; <hi>Reprobation</hi> is a bare <hi>paſſing by; Damnation,</hi> a <hi>puniſhment: Ineptè faciunt, qui Reprobationis decretum, cum Damnatione confundunt; cum hujus cauſa manifeſtà ſit, nempe peccatum; illius vero ſola Dei Voluntas; [Beza.]</hi> They are very ſimple that ſeen ot the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118118:27"/> difference twixt <hi>Reprobation,</hi> and <hi>Damnation;</hi> Gods Will is Cauſe of the firſt; ſinne of the laſt: <hi>Peccatum non eſt Cauſa Rejectionis, ſed eſt Cauſa Damnationis, [Zanchy.]</hi> ſinne is not the Cauſe of <hi>Reprobation,</hi> but of <hi>Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reprobation</hi> is not a <hi>deniall</hi> of <hi>ſufficient Grace,</hi> but a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> of ſuch <hi>ſpeciall Grace,</hi> as <hi>God knoweth would infallibly bring men to Glory:</hi> and this Decree doth not ſhut up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man under a neceſſity of ſinning, or of being dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but it permitteth men volun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arily and freely, to run into damnable ſinnes, and through their voluntary impenitency, to incurre eternall damnation; for the <hi>Sentence</hi> of <hi>Damnation</hi> lays not hold on men, <hi>quà non electi; ſed quà impii,</hi> not as non-elect, but as wicked.</p>
            <p>It is contrary to Gods nature, cauſeleſly, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deſtroy his creatures; but it is not contrary to his nature, to decree out of his mercy, to beſtow Grace and Mercy on ſome; and to Decree, out of the liberty of his Will, to permit others, through their owne volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary default, by abuſing the meanes of <hi>Grace</hi> that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, to fall into eternal miſery; <hi>he hath mercy on whom he will,</hi> Exo. 33. 19. <hi>If man had been created Wicked, or Evill, then God had not had juſt occaſion to puniſh the wickedneſſe, whereof he himſelfe was the Authour, and Maker; but being created good, and having given him power to ſtand, hee may juſtly puniſh him if he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Preterition,</hi> or <hi>Reprobation</hi> it well followeth; <hi>Judas</hi> is <hi>reprobated;</hi> therefore <hi>he will not uſe the meanes,</hi> that God <hi>offereth</hi> for <hi>his ſalvation; but it is not a good Conſequence to ſay; therefore God hath not given him ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient meanes,</hi> or remedies to <hi>eſcape damnation,</hi> were not his owne wicked Will the onely hinderance. <hi>Theſe two Propoſitions may ſtand together; I will, that if Judas repent, and</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118118:27"/> 
               <hi>believe, he ſhall have remiſſion and ſalvation; I will not give unto Judas the gift of Repentance,</hi> or <hi>Faith,</hi> that he may <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſalvation:</hi> As it is ſenceleſſe to ſay, Gods Decree of giving Faith to <hi>Peter,</hi> was ſuſpended till <hi>Peters</hi> Faith, and Repentance; ſo it is as ſenceleſſe, to ſay Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting <hi>Judas</hi> to dye in Unbeliefe, and Impenitency was grounded upon his Unbeliefe and Impenitency.</p>
            <p>It's true the Fathers were ſparing in this Poynt, till that Monſter, <hi>Pelagianiſme</hi> was Midwifed into the World; and yet, <hi>Deus in negotio Predeſtinationis non egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur extra ſe;</hi> and the Cauſe of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is, <hi>ſola Dei Voluntas;</hi> ſo ſayd all the Fathers, and ſo ſay the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches; (for I ſay the <hi>Lutherans</hi> are yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in their <hi>Omnipreſence,</hi> and <hi>fore-ſeene Faith)</hi> then how can there be any conſideration of <hi>fore-ſeene Faith</hi> and <hi>Workes?</hi> God goes out of himſelfe, if he have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>Faith, Perſeverance,</hi> or any thing that is not <hi>intrà ſe:</hi> is it not non-ſence to ſay, the Decree of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is <hi>intrà ſe,</hi> if God have reſpect to any thing <hi>extra ſe?</hi> And if any object, that God doth nothing, therefore not Reprobate without a Reaſon; I ſay, his <hi>Will</hi> is <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſufficient; doe we ſay, and pray, <hi>thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven,</hi> and yet <hi>deny</hi> it in <hi>Predeſtination?</hi> the Pſalmiſt doth prove it true in deſpite of proud man, <hi>Our God hath done whatſoever pleaſed him in Heaven and Earth,</hi> Pſal. 135. 6. <hi>He did worke,</hi> and <hi>he doth worke all things after the Councell of his owne Will,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 5. Rom. 9. 19. Suppoſe that I, with others, come for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to ſuch a Gentlemans houſe, may hee not take them in, and refuſe to afford me that favour, and for no other Reaſon, but becauſe he will not? If I ſhould ſay, Sir, ſhew mee a Reaſon wherefore you reject mee:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118118:28"/> may he not anſwer; it is, becauſe he will not accept me? muſt there needs be a quarrell, or hee may not? So heere, muſt there needs be <hi>infidelity,</hi> evill <hi>Workes, Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne,</hi> or ſome other ill condition in me, or elſe God may not do with his owne as he lift? ſure none will ſay ſo againſt themſelves; then how can they ſuppoſe it ſo of God? The <hi>Maſter,</hi> whoſe Scholers we may, nay wee muſt be, Mat. 20. 15. ſaid, <hi>it was lawfull for him to doe with his owne as hee lifted;</hi> and may not God have the ſame leave? as that Parable ſeems to prove; <hi>Stat pro ratione voluntas,</hi> is moſt proper to Almighty God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reprobation,</hi> by <hi>it ſelfe</hi> conſidered, is no <hi>puniſhment,</hi> therefore it ſuppoſeth no <hi>fault;</hi> the name ſignifieth no more but not to allow of; <hi>ſola voluntas, decretum, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placitum, propoſitum Dei;</hi> all, or any of theſe cannot ſtand with the <hi>fore-ſight of Faith,</hi> or <hi>Infidelity;</hi> good or evill <hi>Workes.</hi> Indeed God foreſees all ſinnes, Originall, and Actuall; it were Atheiſme to deny it; but that any ſin, Originall, or Actuall ought to goe before the firſt Act of God, called <hi>Reprobation,</hi> I utterly deny; let them call <hi>Faith, Infidelity,</hi> good and evill <hi>Workes,</hi> but <hi>Objects, Motives, Reaſons, Circumſtances</hi> conſiderable in Gods <hi>Decree;</hi> yet if they looke into their Logicke, it will let them ſee, that the leaſt of Cauſes, <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non,</hi> is yet a Cauſe; and God, if hee regard any thing, but his owne <hi>Will</hi> in <hi>Election,</hi> or <hi>Reprobation,</hi> muſt goe <hi>extraſe:</hi> to ſay (as they ſay, to ſalve the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God) that he could not <hi>Elect</hi> without looking on man in <hi>maſſa Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and yet that he did not conſider it as any <hi>Reaſon</hi> of his <hi>Decree,</hi> is without <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know my wiſe Adverſaries, the <hi>Black-ſmith,</hi> or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſent abroad that bable, Object againſt theſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118118:28"/> things, (and ſo do the Papiſts, becauſe they will not ſeeme to play the Fooles without Reaſon) that by this it followes the Freedome of mans Will muſt periſh: <hi>Gods Glory is obſcured,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>T. if he puniſh neceſſitated wickedneſſes:</hi> The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Pelagians</hi> are of this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; then a Murtherer, ſaith <hi>Pighius,</hi> when he killeth a man, may be excuſed, becauſe he hath executed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God; then all care, diligence, and endeavour is taken away, if our Thoughts, Words, Deeds be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God; to ſuch I may anſwer, or aske this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Can they doe any thing that God hath not decreed? They are almoſt Atheiſts, that ſay they can; then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, they can doe nothing but it is decreed; Let <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi> anſwer for me, <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>pa.</hi> 6. I wonder, ſaith he, ſpeaking of theſe and other Objections of <hi>Pighius,</hi> that any <hi>Divine</hi> could let ſuch an old Wifes Talecome out of his mouth; Can <hi>Judas</hi> be excuſed of his wicked treaſon againſt our Saviour, becauſe he heard the Lord <hi>fore-tell</hi> his miſchievous deſigne? <hi>John</hi> 13. 21. So then, it is a ſimple, nay it is a <hi>ſinfull thing to excuſe any ſinne, by the eternall or abſolute Decree of God: it is his owne Will, not the Will of God,</hi> that the <hi>miſchiefe-munger,</hi> or the <hi>murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer regards;</hi> he cannot doe otherwiſe; nay but aske him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and hee'l ſay he will not.</p>
            <p>Such, as maintaine <hi>Gods abſolute Decree,</hi> hold neceſſity <hi>infallibilitatis,</hi> not <hi>coactionis;</hi> they ſay that God deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines mans Will; and yet it is Free, as I ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and followes the dictate of its owne Intellect: to reaſon thus, God hath eternally fore-ſeene <hi>Judas</hi> his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, therefore decreed him to eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore <hi>Judas</hi> ſhal infallibly continue impenitent, and at length be damned, is a true inference; but this,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118118:29"/> God hath eternally fore-ſeene <hi>Judas</hi> his impenitency, therefore <hi>Judas</hi> ſhall by coaction, or compulſion of his Will, be made unalterably impenitent, and ſo be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is a falſe Concluſion; The Agent is yet as free, as if God had not foreſeene; <hi>the abſolute will of God to worke faith, repentance, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Peter, maketh not theſe actions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſory,</hi> but maketh the <hi>agent moſt free; for it giveth him that ſpirit,</hi> of which the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>ubi spiritus, ibi libertas:</hi> true and perfect liberty, and Gods Spirit goe both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and <hi>e contra; non-Election denieth men that Grace, which would effectually and infallibly</hi> make them produce good <hi>Actions;</hi> but it <hi>depriveth</hi> them not of their owne <hi>naturall freedome, neither doth it compell them to evill actions; Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Voluntas non tollit potentiam ad oppoſitum;</hi> God hath determined to permit men to faile in attaining eternall life; but he is not Authour of their ſinnes, whereby they incur eternall death.</p>
            <p>In good Actions the Freedome of men Elected is not vaine, though the End be determined; becauſe God hath determined together with the End, that by their free Actions they ſhall attaine it; and in bad their Freedome is not vaine; becauſe thereby their Conſciences are convinced of their guilt; and Gods Juſtice cleared in their damnation.</p>
            <p>Reprobation, and the permiſſion thereto annexed, importeth not a witholding of Grace, neceſſary for the avoyding of ſinne ſo permitted, much leſſe a neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinners to their ſeverall ſinnes; but a withold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all Grace, which would <hi>de facto</hi> be effectuall to the avoyding of ſinne: ſo that <hi>ſinne flowes not from this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Permiſſion, as an Effect, from the Cauſe; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Conſequence, from the Antecedent, neceſſitate infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis;</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118118:29"/> as the Sunne, witholding his Beames, cauſeth not darkneſſe; yet darkneſſe is a Conſequent: Neither doth this Preterition or Reprobation imply a ſubſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Graces, or helpes obtained: but a non-Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Graces, without which God foreſaw, that Reprobates, out of their own <hi>Free-Will,</hi> would infallibly periſh in their ſins: <hi>Deo Reprobante non irrogatur aliquid, quo homo fit deterior: ſed tantùm non irrogatur quo fiat meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or:</hi> man is not made worſer: but he is not made better by this Act of Preterition or Reprobation.</p>
            <p>Nay, there is not only <hi>a bare permiſſive,</hi> but there is alſo <hi>an energeticall,</hi> and operative <hi>Will in God, conjoyned with the permiſſive Will;</hi> and this operative, or energe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Will of God is <hi>apparent</hi> in theſe <hi>ſix Circumſtances:</hi> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">1. God eternally decreeth, and accordingly when ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Actions are committed giveth the ſinner power and uſe of Underſtanding, and Free Will, without which he could not ſinne: 2. God thereby eternally decreed to concurre, and doth concurre <hi>ad materialem actum peccati,</hi> to the ſinne as it is an Action: 3. God decreed the Circumſtances, or Occaſions, good as from God, whereupon he ſaw the ſinner would make evill uſe and ſinne: 4. God decreed to deny the Meanes, that he knew, would have prevented ſuch ſinnes: and offered onely ſuch as he knew the ſinner would abuſe to the committing of ſinne: 5. God li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteth, and ordereth their ſinnes, ſo that they breake forth in no other meaſure, at no other time, upon no other perſons, then himſelfe hath fore-appoynted: 6. God ordereth all theſe ſinnes to his owne Glory, and the good of his Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>moſt ſinfull Actions of man tend to the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:118118:30"/> 
               <hi>of Gods Glory,</hi> either as <hi>Acts of mercy</hi> to the <hi>godly</hi> (in whom ſinne produceth puniſhment; puniſhment Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; Repentance Faith; Faith the Favour of God; and the Favour of God Life, and Salvation) <hi>or as Acts of Juſtice to the Wicked,</hi> in whom ſinne produceth puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; puniſhment, hardneſſe of heart; hardneſſe of heart, incredulity; incredulity, hatred of God; and hatred of God, death and deſtruction: All which is manifeſt in the different effects which ſinne produced in godly <hi>David,</hi> and in ungodly <hi>Pharoah;</hi> as for example, <hi>Davids Murther, and Adultery occaſioned Reproofes, and Corrections from God,</hi> 2. Sam. 12. Pſal. 6. Pſal. 22. <hi>Theſe corrections and puniſhments wrought ſorrow and Repentance in Davids heart,</hi> Pſal. 5. <hi>that Repentance, Faith, and truſt in God,</hi> Pſal. 30. Pſal. 31. Pſal. 52. Pſal. 23. <hi>That Faith and Truſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Love and Favour from God,</hi> Pſal. 27. <hi>and that Love and Favour, an aſſured hope of Life and Salvation,</hi> Pſal. 12. <hi>But Pharaohs oppreſſions provoaked God to ſend his judgements, and plagues upon him; theſe plagues they hardned Pharoahs heart; that hardneſſe of heart cauſed incredulity; that incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity the hatred of God; and that hatred occaſioned Pharaohs ruine and deſtruction in the red Sea,</hi> as it is Exod. 14. Yea the goodneſſe of God made the very drunkeneſſe, and inceſt of <hi>Lot;</hi> the inceſt of <hi>Judah;</hi> the malice of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> the treaſon of <hi>Judas;</hi> and the injuſtice of <hi>Pilate,</hi> Meanes of mans ſalvation; yea even <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, the fountaine of ſinne, and miſery in man, was by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God made a meanes of greater happineſſe to the Godly, then his perſeverance and continuance in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency could have been: For if life had been given, as a reward of our juſt Workes, (ſo the wittieſt of the Schoolemen, <hi>Scotus)</hi> then our Worke being finite could
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118118:30"/> not have merited an infinite reward, the enjoyment whereof but one minute had paſſed our merit; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as life eternall being now conferred upon the faithfull, not by way of Debt, but by the Free Grace and Mercy of God, this infinite Gift is proportioned, not according to the meane merits of the Receiver, but according to the goodneſſe of God the Giver. So that even Sinne it ſelfe, on this manner, that I have ſhewed may be ſaid to be of God. Let a man ſpur forward a lame Horſe, in that he moveth forward, the Rider is Cauſe; but that he halteth he himſelfe is the cauſe: When we ſee the Sun Beames ſhining through a Glaſſe, the Light is from the Sun; the Colour not from the Sun; but from the Glaſſe: For, <hi>talis Actio cum tali defectu,</hi> is not of God; as ſinfull Actions have in them <hi>formalem rationem peccati,</hi> and are oppoſite to the Rule of Gods Law, ſo God nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, nor can be the Cauſer of them; yet is he the Cauſe of that inward or outward naturall Action, wherein this defect of mans Will is found: <hi>Entitas pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae actionis cadit in Voluntatem Divinam;</hi> yet man hath not onely <hi>potentiam in ſe liberam,</hi> but <hi>liberum uſum poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> not onely free power, but alſo free uſe of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as it appeares in Thieves, Adulterers, and the like, who, when there is danger, doe not, yet after do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God is no Enforcer in ſinfull Actions, yet may he be a Decreer, or Permitter,</hi> ſuffering perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s not elected to fall volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily into ſins; to continue volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to their lives end; &amp; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to undergo endleſs miſery in another life. God decreed the permiſſion, &amp; diſpoſing of ſin, which he fore-ſaw upon his permiſſion would be, but he did not decree the effecting, or Exiſtence of it, that it ſhould be; it more
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118118:31"/> appertained to Gods Omnipotent Goodneſſe to draw good out of evill; then not to ſuffer evill to be.</p>
            <p>And as in bad, ſo alſo in good Actions, God not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fore-ſees, that a man will uſe his <hi>Free-Will</hi> well: but wils and preordaines, that he ſhall uſe it well. <hi>It is true, that men juſtified by Gods Predeſtination, by their endeavour and deliberation, may be ſaid to determine themſelves to good Workes; I ſay after Juſtification: but it is God, that moves, and makes them thus to determine themſelves, and doe all theſe things with a Free Will.</hi> This is a ſure Rule; a man doth not that good thing, which by Grace he is able to doe, unleſſe God make him to doe it, as he hath made him able to do it, if he will: <hi>Ad perſeverantiam in Fide &amp; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, non opus eſt nova, &amp; ſpeciali Gratia, ſufficit ad hoc vel quod Naturà habemus, vel quod ſemel per Spiritum adepti ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> to perſeverance in Faith and Grace, there needes no ſpeciall Grace, Nature, or Grace once received is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for this: None have beene ſo bold to ſay thus, but the old <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and later <hi>Semi-Pelagians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, that Chriſt ſaith of ſinfull <hi>Jeruſalem; How often would I have gathered thy Children together, as an Hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her Chickens, and yee would not?</hi> Mat. 23. 37. But <hi>he willed togather them,</hi> not <hi>Voluntate beneplaciti, which cannot be reſiſted, but by his revealed Will, uſing the meanes which might</hi> (had man not falne) <hi>have beene effectuall; that impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency in our Wills comes not from the Creator; but from man that fell from his Creator; and the Will is now ſtarke dead</hi> (as to good Actions) <hi>untill it be enlivened by God:</hi> This dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrine, that all men were redeemed by Chriſt, but not made free, becauſe God diſtributeth his gifts according to the careleſneſſe of ſuch as came to receive them, was an old rotten Hereſie, buried many hundred
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118118:31"/> yeares ſince, and raiſed up againe by the Devill, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the peace of the Church in our dayes.</p>
            <p>To drive this nayle any further, were needleſſe, had I Men to deal with; but my Adverſaries, many of them, are ſuch Beaſts, as fought with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet once over againe, all this I have ſayd ſhall bee poved both by evident Reaſons; and out of the Word of God.</p>
            <p>For 1. I ſay, <hi>God foreſees all Contingent Effects to come, in his own determination of the Cauſes thereof; and therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Contingent Operation of our Will, hee determines it to the Effect.</hi> 2. <hi>Els there ſhould bee two ſeverall beginnings of one, and the ſame Effect,</hi> in as much as Mans Will ſhould begin to work, as ſoon as God; and concur to the Effect willed, as principally as God. 3. <hi>The Will of Man is but Gods Inſtrument;</hi> the Hatchet, the Hammer, whereby God hewes out his own worke; but every one that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth any Inſtrument moves, applies, and determines it to his own will. 4. <hi>The Will of Man is but a ſecondary, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Cauſe, under the firſt Cauſe, which is God,</hi> and exceeds not the meaſure of <hi>ſecond Cauſes;</hi> but if it were not determined by the firſt Cauſe, it ſhould be all one with the firſt Cauſe it ſelfe: Second Cauſes are alwaies mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to their Effects by the Firſt; and in their operations reduced to the motion of one univerſall prime Cauſe, that is God. Therefore it is, the Scriptures ſay, that <hi>the way of man is not in himſelfe, neither is it in man to direct his owne ſteps,</hi> Jer. 10. 28. <hi>It is God that gives a new heart, and puts a new ſpirit in man,</hi> Jer. 31. 33. <hi>God placed the members in mans body, and orders them as it pleaſeth him,</hi> 1. Cor. 12. 18. <hi>It is God that worketh in us, both to will, and to doe of his good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2. 13. <hi>The heart of the King</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118118:32"/> 
               <hi>is in the hand of the Lord, and he turneth it, as it pleaſeth him,</hi> Prov. 21. 1. <hi>He hardened Pharaohs heart,</hi> Exod. 7. 3. <hi>as hard as a ſtone; and he takes away our ſtony hearts, and gives us hearts of fleſh; he hath done, he doth, and he will doe what he will. The will of God was but fulfilled, when Judas did betray Jeſus,</hi> Act. 1. 16. <hi>Herod, Pontius Pilate, and the whole Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of the Jewes, did no more then what God had determined to be done,</hi> Act. 2. 23. and Act. 4. 28. The whole World u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited can doe nothing but what God will; and God is not moved conſequently, by any thing which he as a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Cauſe moves and determines to the Effect; but God himſelfe, antecedently, as a ſuperiour Cauſe, moves and determines the Will of man to the Effect, or that which it wils, be it good or ill.</p>
            <p>Therefore it follows, <hi>God is not conſequently moved by the good or ill uſe of the Free Will of man:</hi> therefore <hi>the good uſe of mans Will foreſeen moved not God to Elect him, and the evill uſe of mans Will foreſeen was not the Cauſe that God Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated him:</hi> Therefore God had no Antecedent Will to ſave the Reprobate, if they would, by their Free Will, receive and uſe his Grace aright: therefore Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree touching the Salvation, and Reprobation of men, is laſtly, and finally, reſolved into his owne pure Will.</p>
            <p>Univerſaliſt; thou telleſt me of the love of God to Man; and in that thou telleſt me true; for if all the World were full of Bookes; if all the men in the world were Writers; and if all the water in the Sea were Inke: yet the Bookes would bee written, the Writers weary, the Inke ſpent, and yet the Love of God to us poorely expreſſed: but then let me tell thee, that this Love of God to man ſhould make a reflection towards this Sun, and move man to love God againe, and nothing but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118118:32"/> God; and himſelfe for this God, that loved him when he was nothing, ſubmitting himſelfe wholy and ſoly to the Will of God.</p>
            <p>There are foure degrees of Love: Firſt, a man loves himſelfe for his owne ſake, for he is fleſh, and ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally can love nothing but himſelfe; but when he ſees, that he cannot ſubſiſt without God, then neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels him, but for his owne ſake ſtill, to flie to God; <hi>and when he has begun to love God, though but for his owne ſake, and begins withall to taſte and ſee how ſweet God is, then he loves God no more for his owne ſake; but for Gods ſake;</hi> and when he has attained to this third ſtep, <hi>to love God for Gods ſake, he ſtaies there, and ſtrives</hi> (if it be poſſible for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to obtaine this heavenly happyneſſe heere on Earth) <hi>to love himſelfe onely for Gods ſake: Thus the true love of God ſhould both begin, and end onely in God: like a Circle, which begins, and ends in it ſelfe:</hi> Now let Mr. <hi>T.</hi> take heed, how hee preach againſt this abſolute Will, and Power in God; and plead his owne Faith and Workes, <hi>leſt God at length be avenged on him; God hath leaden heeles, but iron hands; he ſeemes to winke with his eyes,</hi> but it is as Gunners uſe, that they may hit ſurer, when they ſhoot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen</hi> in his ſecond Booke againſt <hi>Celſus</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>A certaine man gave counſell to his friend that was ſick, not to ſend for the Phyſitian, becauſe</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>it is already appoynted by Deſtiny, either that thou ſhalt recover of this Diſeaſe; or that thou ſhalt not; if it be appoynted by God, or by thy Deſtiny, that thou ſhalt recover, thou ſhalt then not need the Phyſitian; if it be not appoynted by God; if it be not thy Deſtiny to recover, the Phyſitian, though hee come, cannot helpe thee; wherefore whether God have decreed thou ſhalt recover, or not, the Phyſitian will be called in vaine.</hi> Another, by the like Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118118:33"/> diſſwaded his Friend from Marriage: <hi>Thou wilt marry a Wife</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>to beget Children; but if it be thy Deſtiny to have Children, thou ſhalt have them without a Wife; if it be not thy Deſtiny, it will nothing further thee to marry a Wife; for whatſoever Deſtiny hath decreed in this kinde will come to paſſe; it is in vaine therefore to marry a Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus wicked men deride, and would rather that blind-man-buffle in the World, then that God deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine every Action and Event; or fix his Decree. But the firſt did ſend for the Phyſitian; and the ſecond did marry a Wife: <hi>Hee us'd a wiſer Argument,</hi> who told them, <hi>that God having Predeſtinated Men to ſuch Ends, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated alſo, that they ſhould uſe the Means:</hi> The ſick man might ſafely anſwer; <hi>nay rather if God have Decreed I ſhall recover; therefore I will ſend for the Phyſitian, that by his means I may attaine to that which God hath Decreed.</hi> Thus <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> had <hi>fifteen years added to his life,</hi> by uſing the meanes; and yet he's a Devill that denies, God did, from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, determine the certaine number of his dayes: And that other might anſwer; <hi>if God have appoynted I ſhall have children, ſeeing it can, or ought to come to paſſe by no other meanes, I will marry a Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this abſolute <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> we are far enough from the Stoicks <hi>Fate;</hi> they ſubjected God himſelfe to <hi>Fate;</hi> we ſubject <hi>Fate,</hi> that is the neceſſity of things to Gods moſt <hi>Free-Will;</hi> they, under the name of <hi>Fate,</hi> underſtood a neceſſary connexion of naturall Cauſes and Effects; we teach that God can, and often doth ſuſpend theſe Effects, and works beſides, nay, againſt Nature: The Stoicks tooke away all <hi>contingency;</hi> Wee admit <hi>contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency</hi> in reſpect of <hi>ſecond Cauſes,</hi> but we ſay there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>preſcience</hi> in the <hi>firſt Cauſe;</hi> all things are ordered
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118118:33"/> by the providence of God. Indeed the <hi>Turks,</hi> out of their obſtinate beliefe of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> brutiſhly contemne all kindes of dangers; for they ſay, that as ſoone as man comes out of his mothers Wombe to enjoy the light of the world, God writes in his forehead all the good or evill that ſhall happen unto him; and particularly of what death hee ſhall dye; the neceſſity whereof (they ſay) no humane power can avoyd: and hence it came to paſſe, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1611. there died of the Plague in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> 200000. in five months, every day 12 or 15 hundred, for they will not turn away from a body dead of this diſeaſe; nor forbeare to viſit their Friends being infected; no, they conclude it contrary to all reaſon, that any good, or evill can bee prevented, ſeeing every thing is pre-ordayned of God. But wee Chriſtians are taught better things; that we ſhould not ſo fooliſhly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the ſecret Counſells of God, as to make them altogether agreeable to our blockiſh Reaſon.</p>
            <p>I might enlarge my ſelfe on this Subject; I want not matter to ſtop the wideſt mouth among my neighbors: but I will draw towards a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Reader, I pray thee ſeriouſly conſider, if both the <hi>Supra-lapſarian,</hi> and the <hi>Sub-lapſarian,</hi> may not meete, and ſweetly ſet forth the Mercy, and Juſtice of God: the <hi>Supra-lapſarians</hi> ſay, that in the <hi>firſt</hi> Act of <hi>Reprobation,</hi> God doth all for himſelf only; in the <hi>ſecond,</hi> that is <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> he does all for <hi>ſin:</hi> in this laſt the <hi>Supra-lapſarian,</hi> and the <hi>Sub-lapſarian</hi> ſay, that God doth the ſecond for Sin; I ſee not why he may not ſay, hee doth the firſt for Himſelfe, and ſo be in that a <hi>Supra-lapſarian:</hi> but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene Faith, and Works in the firſt Act of God, claſhes <hi>ex Diametro,</hi> againſt the Word of God. I know in God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118118:34"/> there is no firſt, or laſt; <hi>prius</hi> or <hi>poſterius;</hi> but yet for our better underſtanding, wee may conceive the <hi>Decrees</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> and <hi>Preterition,</hi> in order <hi>of priority, antecedent</hi> to the <hi>permiſſion of ſin,</hi> and therefore much more to the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceive, the Queſtion is not, whether God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw what <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Bad</hi> would doe; who dares doubt of that; but whether the <hi>Different Actions of Men, foreſeen,</hi> cauſed the <hi>Different Decrees, of their Election, and Preteriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> indeed it is impoſſible, but that God ſhould ſee all things at once; therefore he could not <hi>Predeſtinate, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, without previſion, and permiſsion of ſin;</hi> but even <hi>Originall ſin alone, though foreſeene,</hi> could not bee Cauſe, why <hi>Peter was Predeſtinated, and Judas not,</hi> ſeeing it was foreſeen in both, and made both <hi>ex aequo Reprobabiles;</hi> therefore it was <hi>Gods will,</hi> that made a difference, and not any <hi>Originall ſin.</hi> God determined to permit the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie of Men, and Angels; to damne ſome of Men; all the Apoſtate Angells: yet God might have Elected <hi>Cain,</hi> or <hi>Judas,</hi> unto Glory without injuſtice; and paſſed by <hi>Peter;</hi> God forbid, we ſhould ſay, <hi>the Divine Will was determined,</hi> and could not doe otherwiſe: yet <hi>Cain, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> were equally guilty of Originall ſin.</p>
            <p>Wee grant not; that by this <hi>abſolute Reprobation,</hi> God Decreeth, that Men not Predeſtinated, ſhould unavoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably ſinne, that ſo they may certainly be damned; but we grant, that God <hi>foreknoweth, perſons not elected</hi> will vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily commit thoſe ſinnes, for which hee intends to damne them: but <hi>Negative Reprobation neither procureth, nor ſuppoſeth any ſinne; as damnation doth: The Decrees of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding men out of Heaven, and tormenting them in Hell, are different.</hi> I ſay then, that even <hi>Judas,</hi> notwithſtanding
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118118:34"/> his <hi>Reprobation,</hi> might have been ſaved, had hee not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued voluntarily impenitent; if any ſay, he could not, yea but I ſay he would not; <hi>there was by Gods Act of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, no neceſſity of coaction impoſed on his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if any object; that the <hi>ſalvation of all</hi> were more for Gods glory; To this I anſwer, God is not to learne of us what makes moſt for his Glory; hee could have upheld the <hi>Angels, Adam; ſaved all,</hi> and every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; but he did not, he doth not: therefore this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Decree to bring but <hi>ſome to ſalvation,</hi> and permit <hi>others infallibly to fall,</hi> doth make moſt for his glory. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Alphonſus</hi> K. of <hi>Caſtile</hi> ſayd, God might have made his Works, and done many things much better then he did; but it was <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> take you heed, Mr. <hi>T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt not omit, how that the 39. <hi>Articles</hi> agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the whole <hi>Clergie of England, anno</hi> 1562. <hi>for eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of Conſent touching true Religion,</hi> are flat op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to theſe Opinions of our Univerſaliſts: they are againſt the 10. <hi>Article,</hi> which ſayth; <hi>That man, ſince the fall of Adam, hath no Free Will, or Power, to doe any thing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and acceptable unto God:</hi> they are againſt the 11. <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>Juſtification is not for any of our own works, or deſervings:</hi> they are againſt the 12. <hi>Article,</hi> which ſayth, <hi>Good works are onely fruits of Faith, and follow after Juſtification; and by Conſequence, Election:</hi> they are againſt the 17. <hi>Article,</hi> which calls <hi>Predeſtination to life, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Purpoſe of God, wherely, before the Foundations of the World were layd, he hath conſtantly Decreed, by his Counſell ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to us, to deliver from curſe and damnation thoſe, whom hee hath choſen in Chriſt out of mankinde, and to bring them by Chriſt to everlaſting ſalvation, as veſſels made to honour, &amp;c. So then the Foundation of Predeſtination to life, is the purpoſe</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118118:35"/> 
               <hi>of God, and his Counſell; not foreſeene Faith, whereby hee hath conſtantly Decreed (Predeſtination is immutable) to deliver from Curſe thoſe only, whom he had choſen in Chriſt; hee had no purpoſe to ſave all; and they are called Veſſels made to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which implies other Veſſels made to diſhonour.</hi> If Mr. <hi>T.</hi> be a Miniſter, then hee might remember, that hee once conſented to the truth of theſe <hi>Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, <hi>Arminius in his Declaration to the States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and West-Friſland,</hi> endeavoureth to prove, by 20. <hi>Arg. That God hath not Decreed abſolutely to ſave certaine particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars;</hi> And <hi>Bertius,</hi> his Scholar, ſaith; <hi>This abſolute Decree openeth a gate on this ſide to a diſſolute life; on that ſide to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation.</hi> They ſay further, <hi>That the Opinion of preciſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, without reſpect of foreſeene Faith in the Elect, overthron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all Religion.</hi> But, Reader, thou mayſt remember, that theſe two are much like thoſe Artiſts, that found out the Trade they profeſſed; they are not the Children of our Mother: both <hi>Arminians,</hi> and our <hi>Univerſaliſts,</hi> make a deſperate uſe of this Doctrine: but the Doctrine it ſelf is no deſperate Doctrine, or Doctrine of deſperation, but of Heavenly conſolation; as wee read in our 17. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle;</hi> the words are theſe. <hi>The godly conſideration of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, and our Election in Chriſt, is full of ſweet, pleaſant, and unſpeakable comfort to godly perſons, and ſuch as feele in themſelves the working of the ſpirit of Chriſt, mortifying the works of the fleſh, and their earthly members, and drawing up their mindes to high and heavenly things; as well becauſe it doth greatly eſtabliſh and confirme the Faith of eternall Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be enjoyed through Chriſt, as becauſe it doth fervently kindle their love towards God, &amp;c.</hi> They that draw deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Concluſions, becauſe of Gods Decree, are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that Article; and I am ſure our Doctrine of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:118118:35"/> 
               <hi>is a ſavour of life unto life; if it prove a ſavour of death unto death,</hi> it is onely to ſuch as pervert the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Holy Scriptures to their owne <hi>deſtruction,</hi> 2. Pet. 3. 16. But the Doctrine of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaliſts,</hi> which makes Gods <hi>Election</hi> depend upon the <hi>Will of man,</hi> which may <hi>totally, and finally fall from Grace,</hi> is a moſt <hi>deſperate Doctrine,</hi> and deprives a Chriſtian of all comfort, both in life, and death; a weake and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full foundation, to build the ſalvation of man (be it but in part, or in poynt of <hi>Perſeverance)</hi> upon himſelfe.</p>
            <p>To reconcile <hi>Gods ſecret, and revealed Will,</hi> becauſe we ſhall be <hi>judged</hi> by the evidence of his <hi>revealed Will, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his ſecret Will;</hi> and though <hi>formal is ratio peccati,</hi> without all queſtion, is not from God; yet how far he ſuffers, or ſets on Sinners (ſeeing he muſt not be outed in any humane Actions, and Events, which are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or accompanied with ſuch Circumſtances) I ſay theſe two ſtumble mee moſt; and though (I thanke God) he hath given me ſome ſatisfaction; yet I believe he is out, that expects a plaine Reaſon; or to prove all things in Scriptures by evident Demonſtrations: <hi>Faith muſt believe what Sence cannot conceive; it is a Chriſtian mans honour, that he over-reacheth Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for a Colophon, or Period to this point of <hi>Predeſtination;</hi> I will ſet down three, or foure Examples, which if they do not <hi>probare,</hi> yet they may ſerve a little <hi>illuſtrare;</hi> therefore I ſay thus: Suppoſe a Lord ſet 20. men on worke, upon condition that if they do his will, they ſhall be all Lords, even Co-heires with his owne Son; if they do it not, they ſhall ſuffer untill they give ſatisfaction: On ten of theſe twenty he ſet his affections ſo far, that if they did miſcarry, he would take a courſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118118:36"/> to deliver them from the danger; they all do quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Lords Command; therefore hee ſent his onely Son, who both did his Fathers Will, which they ſhould have done; ſuffered for that they did not, or did amiſſe; and gave ſufficient ſatisfaction, which the Father accepts, as it was intended by the Son, for them ten, on whom he ſet his firſt Love; but as for the other, hee ſuffers them to periſh in Priſon, or to lye there untill they pay that which can never be paid. Can theſe laſt accuſe their Lord of <hi>Injuſtice?</hi> Or can the firſt ten con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, becauſe their Lord hath ſet his love upon them, therefore they may be careleſſe? Nay rather, they will be carefull, and fearefull to offend ſo kinde, and loving a Lord. I know, <hi>ſimilitudo non currit quatuor pedibus:</hi> yet this I take to be not far from the Caſe 'twixt God and Man: but this Example is to be underſtood of Man in that condition, God Created him; for if conſidered in that condition, into which he caſt himſelfe, then hee is juſtly condemned, for not doing that, which now hee cannot doe: For ſuppoſe, the Parliament command me to come to <hi>London,</hi> and I can ride further, but becauſe I will not doe the Parliaments Commands, I cut one of my legs off, or lame my ſelfe, and then plead, I cannot come; may not the Parliament yet juſtly command me to come, though then I cannot come, becauſe when they commanded mee I might have com'd? Mr. <hi>T.</hi> dare not ſpeake againſt the Parliament in ſuch a caſe; but I can ſhew how deſperately Hee did ſpeake againſt God, if he dare offer to condemne any man for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which, in this condition, hee cannot doe; as if God were bounden to cure us, when we have wounded, or killed our ſelves: Indeed <hi>the Father ran to meet his ſon</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118118:36"/> 
               <hi>afar off,</hi> but he was not bound to go one foot from home. Suppoſe; two Travellers come to my houſe; I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive one; or both; or neither of both: that compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>two poore people,</hi> is not ſo proper, for we were <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in a <hi>Rich Condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe; <hi>Two Houſes built upon the ſame Ground; Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Timber, Stone, Workemanſhip, and all alike, able to ſtand twenty yeares, if no Stormes or Tempeſts touch them: But the Raine fell, the Flouds came, the Windes blew, and beat upon the Houſes; yet the Builder having reſolved to repair, and prop one of them, it fell not; the other he left to it ſelfe, and it ſoon tumbled downe: was the Maſter bound to uphold them both, becauſe he built them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe; <hi>Two Candles burning by the ſame light; a blaſt of winde blowes out both of them; I come inſtantly, and light the one, and it burnes againe; the other I will not light, ſo it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver burnes again; was I bound to light both of them?</hi> Let us give God that ſame liberty which we take: <hi>Audax Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheti genus;</hi> ſee the boldneſſe of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> that would faine enter an Action againſt God Almighty, if they could tell in what Court; for that this <hi>Potter uſeth his Clay, as he pleaſeth; and hath not made all, Veſſels of Honour,</hi> as they would have him: yea, and which is worſt of all, they are ſo addicted, or rather wedded to their own conceites, that they can hardly with patience indure, to heare the reaſonable Opinion of others, contrary to their owne: Every Sentence in the Scriptures makes for them, like the <hi>Foole</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> that thought, every ſhip in the Haven was his owne: they will hold the <hi>Concluſion,</hi> what Arguments ſoever are alledged to prove the contrary: Thus zeale miſled is like mettall in a blinde horſe, which is his owne; or his Riders ruine.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:118118:37"/>
            <p> They love the Children of their Braines, better then the Children of their Bodies; ſo that when they have <hi>conceived miſchiefe, and brought forth an Idol,</hi> or an idle conceit of their owne fancying, it groweth up with them, it delighteth them, and they rejoyce in their own inventions, perſwading themſelves; <hi>that now the Lord will bee good unto them,</hi> ſeeing they have found out a Truth; as <hi>Micha</hi> ſuppoſed, when hee had got a <hi>graven Image,</hi> an <hi>Ephod,</hi> a <hi>Teraphim,</hi> and a <hi>Wandring Levite,</hi> Judg. 17. 5. 11. for this their <hi>Device,</hi> eſpecially if it be painted with ſome colour of holy Scripture, they eſteem as an <hi>Image,</hi> come downe from <hi>Jupiter,</hi> Acts 19. 35. <hi>as a Doctrine from Heaven it ſelfe; and hence forward all the bleſſings that they injoy, flow from this Opinion, that they hold: thus they burne incenſe to the Queene of Heaven,</hi> Jer. 44. 17. <hi>the Idol that they have made after their owne hearts:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will loſe their life rather, then their Religion, which they will defend with tooth and naile; They will Preach for it, as <hi>Hannaniah</hi> did for his <hi>falſe-hoods,</hi> Jer. 28. 11. They will diſpute for their Opinions, as the <hi>Epicureans,</hi> and <hi>Stoicks</hi> did, Acts 17. 18. and write Books in defence of them, as <hi>Shemaiah</hi> did, Jer. 29. 25. and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, if it be in their power, all that contradict them, as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did in defence of his Idolatry, 1. Kings 13. 4. whatſoever is ſpoken out of the Word of God againſt them, they will not heare, no more then the Jewes would the Word of the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Jer. 44. 16. being as hardly induced to thinke it no truth, that their owne wit hath diſcovered, as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> to thinke them no Gods, that were made with hands, Acts 19. 26. <hi>Aſeduced ſpirit hath deceived them,</hi> as that did <hi>Ahab,</hi> when he fell at <hi>Ramoth,</hi> in <hi>Gilead,</hi> 1 Kings
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118118:37"/> 22. 21. <hi>ſo that they cannot deliver their owne ſoules, nor ſay, is there not a lie in my right hand?</hi> Iſa. 44. 20. <hi>They are blinde, and, which is worſe, they will not ſee; fooliſh Prophets, that follow their owne ſpirit,</hi> Ezek. 13. 3.</p>
            <p>What pitty is it, that this <hi>Viper</hi> ſhould <hi>creep</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon the <hi>body</hi> of our Church; and yet <hi>the hand of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> (I hope for want of information) <hi>hath not ſhaken it into the fire? Uſque quò, Domine? Uſque quò?</hi> how long Lord? how long? all thoſe things are come upon us, and yet there is none that knowes how long, Pſal. 74. 9. 10. It is our parts, to pray; <hi>thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> but even the Lord for Chriſts ſake, when it is his bleſſed Will, deliver this Church from the effects of <hi>blinde zeale,</hi> and <hi>over-bold devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have ſet downe ſome of the Opinions of the Brethren in the Goſpel, about us; all their Opinions it is impoſſible to relate; they cannot tell their own Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; they hold any thing, but <hi>the Truth.</hi> A certain <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician,</hi> in reading a Lecture to his Scholars, was quite out; ſo hee asked them if they underſtood him; no, replied they; Indeed I wonder not, ſaid he, <hi>nam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go meipſum non intelligo,</hi> for I underſtand not my ſelfe: the <hi>Brethren</hi> are as much out, as this <hi>Mathematitian,</hi> and may ſay on the ſame maner. A Neighbour, not a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night ſince, diſcourſing with Mr. <hi>T.</hi> told him; he ought not to take the Scriptures alwaies in a <hi>literall ſence:</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid; <hi>he was a Door; a Vine;</hi> vet he was <hi>neither of both, in a literall ſence:</hi> he called the <hi>Bread, his Body;</hi> yet it was <hi>not literally his Body:</hi> Mr. <hi>T.</hi> made anſwer, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, when he ſaid ſo, clapt his hand on his <hi>Body,</hi> and ſaid; <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum, This is my Body;</hi> but hee meant it not of the <hi>Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118118:38"/>
            <p> They ſay; <hi>Affrica ſemper aliquid apportat novi;</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia</hi> abounds as much with <hi>Monſtrous Opinions; as Affrica with Monſters:</hi> and the <hi>Fruits of theſe evill Trees are as bad, as thoſe, that grow upon the banks of the Dead Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Stranger can ſcarce ride twixt <hi>Bridge,</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi> but he may heare, or ſee the Country all ſet on fire: our parts of <hi>Lynſey</hi> vomit out flames as faſt, as <hi>Veſuvius;</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> againſt the <hi>Son;</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> againſt the <hi>Father;</hi> the <hi>Husband</hi> againſt his <hi>Wife;</hi> and the <hi>Wife</hi> againſt her <hi>Husband;</hi> the <hi>Brother</hi> would betray the <hi>Brother</hi> to death; <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Neighbours</hi> are even ready to eat one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Warres,</hi> and <hi>Warlike Opinions,</hi> as if the Times, that Chriſt foretold, had overtaken us.</p>
            <p>At firſt; The <hi>Netherlands</hi> received the infection of this <hi>peſtilent Doctrine</hi> from <hi>Britaine,</hi> by <hi>Pelagius;</hi> and now at laſt <hi>Britaine</hi> hath received the ſame <hi>infection</hi> from the <hi>Netherlands</hi> by <hi>Arminius.</hi> The <hi>Peach-tree</hi> brought out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and planted in <hi>Italy, of ranke poyſon, became pleaſant fruit:</hi> but the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Arminian Opinions,</hi> brought out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and planted upon our <hi>Heaths,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, mad <hi>Hylanders,</hi> have a quite contrary effect: for the practiſes of the Brethren paſſe, and repaſſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and <hi>Arminians;</hi> all but <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> in a ſuper-ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative degree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nero</hi> ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, that he might ſing the <hi>Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Troy, in ſuo genere;</hi> in kind, or in its proper colours; he that hath a minde to ſing <hi>Lachrymae,</hi> in a ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing tune, may ſee a ſad example with us. Let a man but looke into the Townes all about Mr. <hi>T.</hi> and he may ſee, or heare them brawle and brangle; ſo ſoone as they ariſe, and ſo they continue till they go to bed; ſuch Diviſions, and Sub-diviſions, as cannot but make our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:118118:38"/> Enemies to laugh, and ous Friends to weepe.</p>
            <p>The Church of God is now in two Extreames, <hi>a floud and a fire, in a floud of teares,; and yet on fire in her different affections;</hi> alas, that neither <hi>this floud</hi> can quench <hi>that fire;</hi> nor <hi>any fire,</hi> can dry <hi>this floud. The Diviſions of Simeon; the Diviſions of Levi; the Diviſions of Simeon againſt Levi; and the diviſions of Levi among themſelves, who is able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with dry? a man cannot thinke of, as hee ought without without wet eyes.</hi> The <hi>Diviſions</hi> of <hi>Reuben</hi> doe pierce the very ſoule of the <hi>Mother</hi> that <hi>bore him;</hi> and there is none of all the Children, that ſhee hath brought forth, able to comfort their Mother, that is even <hi>ſick at heart, and ſits by the high way ſide, begging helpe of every one that paſſeth by.</hi> Come hither, <hi>Heraclytus;</hi> ſtay Travailer, and weep with us. If any man would tell wonders in his own, let him come firſt into our Country, and there he may ſee that, which no good Chriſtian can deſire, or delight to ſee.</p>
            <p>I have read of one, who being borne blind, he had his ſight given him by his Prayers to God; but then hee ſaw ſo many wickedneſſes, that hee deſired of God to be blind againe; and if the ſtory tell truth, it was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Was it then ſuch an Age, as God hath reſerved us to live in? Our Mother is ſore ſicke of a <hi>Convulſion;</hi> pulld all to peeces, on a pitifull maner; like an Oake, that is cleft in ſunder with Wedges made out of its own body. <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of a <hi>beautifull Damoſell,</hi> whom a company of yong men contended for to be their Bride; they would all of them have had her, but they could not agree, that any one of the ſhould enjoy her; therfore they cut her all to peeces, and tooke each one a part; ſo then they all of them had her, and yet they none of them had her: <hi>Religion is that beautifull Damoſell,</hi> whom <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:118118:39"/> 
               <hi>Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, Arminians, Univerſaliſts,</hi> and other Schiſmatiks ſay they ſtrive for; but the truth is, they cut poore <hi>Religion</hi> all to pieces; and each one of them have a part, but none of them have <hi>pure Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any man had loſt his <hi>Religion,</hi> he might once have found it in <hi>Poland;</hi> afterward in <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> but now in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe it is vaniſhed out of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medaea</hi> cut her childe in pieces; a cruell Mother; but that Children ſhould cut their Mother in pieces, Ah curſed Children! Woe is me that ever I bore you, may may our Mother the Church ſay to ſuch churliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; as the Prophet Jer. of his Mother, Jer. 15. 10. Surely <hi>bloudy Children have you been unto me,</hi> may the Church ſay unto ſuch; as <hi>Zipporah</hi> to her <hi>Husband,</hi> when ſhe <hi>threw the Childes foreskin at his feet,</hi> Exod. 4. 23. <hi>Call me not NAOMI, that is a beautifull Church, but call mee MARAH,</hi> may our Mother ſay, <hi>for the Lord hath dealt bitterly with me,</hi> Ruth 1. 20. <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt K. of <hi>England,</hi> being in his Fathers life time a diſobedient Child, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to meet his Fathers dead body, Royally adorned for the Buriall, according to the Majeſty of his State, the very Corpſe (as it were abhorring, and accuſing him for his unnaturall cruelties) guſhed forth bloud; whereat <hi>Richard</hi> pierced with remorſe melted into a floud of tears, on a moſt penitent manner: But we may ſee the wounds of our Mother, the Church, as <hi>wide</hi> as in the <hi>Warres,</hi> if not as <hi>bloudy,</hi> yet as <hi>deadly,</hi> and yet her hard hearted Children have no remorſe or pitty on their poore Mother, the Church. <hi>Goe to the Iſles of Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tim, and ſee; and ſend unto Kedar, enquire of all the Nations round about us, if any Children uſe their Mother on ſuch a manner,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:118118:39"/> Jer. 2. 10. Eies, diſtill teares; Heart, drop down bloud, if thou haſt any ſence or feeling of the ſad ſufferings of thy ſorrowfull Mother, that is not eaten up, but wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried of her Children, <hi>ſaevientes inter ſe,</hi> raging among themſelves, by ſuch curſed cruell meanes to kill their Mother; as if ſome of the old <hi>Danes;</hi> nay rather ſome old rotten <hi>Hereticks</hi> were raiſed from death to life, to ruine <hi>England.</hi> For a houſe to be on fire in one part, is pittifull; but to be on fire in every part, it is a fearefull thing. There were never ſuch things ſeene in <hi>England,</hi> ſince it was a Nation, as the Iſraelites ſaid, when they ſaw the ſcattered limbs, and pieces of the Levites Wife, Judges 19. 30. The <hi>Red,</hi> and <hi>White Roſes</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> never had the like; nor the two <hi>Lions</hi> of either <hi>Nation, Gold,</hi> and <hi>Gules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is he not rightly named Jacob, ſaid Eſau of his brother? for he hath ſupplanted me &amp;c.</hi> Gen. 27. 36. And are they not rightly called <hi>Univerſaliſts?</hi> for, (beſides that they ſeeke to ſupplant us) like the <hi>Phariſees, they compaſſe ſea and land, to make their Proſelites as univerſall, as their Opinions; and they make them</hi> (if it were poſſible) <hi>worſe then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of their practiſes in ſpreading their Opinions, I touched in my Preface; but yet (that the Subject may be ſutable to the Title, I gave it at the beginning) let me a little further ſhew the Reader their ordinary cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to catch ſuch as are willing to be deceived, and to confront Miniſters: therefore thus.</p>
            <p>If there bee any that loves not, or likes not, or liſt to fall out, or can by any means be drawn to quarrel with his Miniſter, there's hopes of him: ſome of the Brethren ſet upon him to heare Mr. <hi>T.</hi> whom they extoll to the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:118118:40"/> heavens; whither being come, hee is welcomed, taken to his houſe, where they club; and hee is entertained to a cup of Ale, and ſuch newes as they have, or would have: how much Ale hath beene uſually ſent for on a Sabaoth, in one afternoone, I have been told, and could hardly beleeve: all are Fellows alike; and this Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity is a ſound Argument to prove the truth of their Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Then they appoint a meeting at ſome Town there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts; the Brethren give notice of it far and neere; and there is a generall Aſſembly of Men, Women, Boyes, and Wenches; Mr. <hi>T. speaks,</hi> (ſo they call it) either in the Church, or in a private Houſe, Chayre, or Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or without Dores, the ſame things, over, and over again; as if the Brethren had beſought him, as the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> did <hi>Paul, to preach the ſame words next Sabaoth day,</hi> Act. 13. 42. For be the Text whatſoever it wil, he ſhakes hands with it immediatly; they but meet, and part. And the truth is, theſe meetings are ſo ſtrong an Argument, to prove their Opinions, that no one man; nay, no one Town is able to Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Up goe the Miniſters Lifes, and Doctrine, among the Brethren, and Siſters; they cannot edifie by ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; another Preaches not Chriſt; a third, falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and then they conſider, what affronts are fitteſt to be offered to any of them. <hi>Aladine,</hi> Prince of <hi>Dran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giana</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> built a beautifull Pallace, in a pleaſant Valley; which having furniſhed, and fitted with all things, that might raviſh the eye, or care; he promiſed this <hi>Paradiſe</hi> (ſo they calld it) to his Partizans, if they would doe this, or that miſchiefe, againſt ſome <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Lord,</hi> that lived about him: ſo alſo my backe-friend,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:118118:40"/> by his fooles Paradiſe <hi>of Univerſall Grace, offered to all effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually,</hi> ſets wicked men on worke to commit many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes againſt the <hi>Miniſters</hi> that live about him; I ſay, he ſets on ſuch, as in their fortunes can hardly be worſer; or in their manners wickeder And yet they crack con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, that they are ſet on, and ſent by Authority, and abuſe <hi>their Names,</hi> whom they are unworthy to name; they ſay, ſuch ſent them, who are <hi>Gentlemen of Honour,</hi> and as much <hi>Honeſty;</hi> whom, I am ſure, will not own them.</p>
            <p>Scarce one of all the Brethren, and Siſters, but are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Enemies to their owne, and all the Miniſters they know, or know not; they are <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and <hi>ſhepheards are an abomination unto them,</hi> Gen. 46. 34. But Mr. <hi>T.</hi> drives a dainty trade; we fetch our Tithes, and well are we, if we can have them for fetching; they cary to Mr. <hi>T.</hi> &amp;c. and if this Devill bee caſt out, the hopes of his gaine is gone.</p>
            <p>I might ſhew their uncivill behaviours in hearing the Word of God; I have Preached to men 25 years; now to Monſters, that make ſtrange faces; laughing, jeering, and chatting in the Church. I have read of a woman that being left poore at the death of her Husband, the Devill appeared unto her, and promiſed to make her rich, upon condition, that ſhee ſhould performe theſe 3. things. 1. <hi>Entice Church men to be nought with her:</hi> 2. <hi>Take poore people in o'th day, as if ſhe meant to give them lodging; and turne them out at night:</hi> 3. <hi>That ſhe would do, as theſe doe themſelves, and ſet their children and ſervants to doe, diſturb the Miniſter in praying and preaching in the Church.</hi> Thus are they like the <hi>Dog,</hi> that will neither eat Hay himſelf, nor ſuffer the Horſe to eat. I cannot tell how more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to compare them, then to the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reticks, <hi>Bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:118118:41"/> whom they called thus for their beaſtly behaviour.</p>
            <p>And if any Miniſter dare bee ſo bold, as to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their proceedings, then Mr. <hi>T.</hi> engages all his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers againſt him; as he did engage them againſt mee: they are the words of that <hi>blacke Bill,</hi> ſent abroad under his hand: Hee preaches falſe Doctrine; and they muſt undertake to prove it true, by Arguments, <hi>a fuſtibus,</hi> drawne from their fiſts: Indeed ſo did <hi>John Becold,</hi> the Taylor of <hi>Leyden,</hi> after King, and Captaine of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> at <hi>Munſter;</hi> and ſo did <hi>David George</hi> of <hi>Delfe,</hi> that damned Heretick: I wonder how he can tread ſo right in the ſteps of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> reading ſo few Books, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Bible; for, by relation, he takes as much pains in the Pulpit, as any man living; as little out of it; but this it is, to be inſpired by the <hi>ſame ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all their other practiſes, their publicke Meetings are moſt offenſive; and may in time prove as pernicious to the Common-wealth, as they are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to the Church: the Lord God grant that Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may look to it in time, that we may ſleep quietly in our beds by night, and not be affrighted by ſuch Fellows, <hi>de faece plebis,</hi> if we walk abroad by day. For multitudes to meet, on this maner, at a little Towne, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Miniſter, and other Inhabitants, is ſuch a courſe, as was uſed at <hi>Mulhus,</hi> in <hi>Turingia,</hi> and at <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> among the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> it never was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong good Chriſtians. Indeed <hi>Robert le Bruce</hi> K. of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> admitted of women and boyes, to ſupply the rooms of trained Souldiers in his neceſſities; and though hee thereby got the day: yet I hope, that wee who fight the battels of the Lord of Hoſts, ſhall never be defeated by ſuch a ſimple policy; a rowt of ſilly Women, ignorant
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:118118:41"/> Men, and a rabble of Girles, and Boyes.</p>
            <p>For my own, and my good Neighbours ſake, I muſt ſignifie, that there are in our Town but 2. conſtant Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Mr. <hi>T.</hi> that go to him: when he comes to them, then he may have 4. or 5. more, but not many; not one Husband-man (that I know of) will goe out of doores to heare him; I thinke deſires not hee ſhould come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their doores, except one, who is almoſt deafe and blinde, and came ſcarce this halfe yeer to hear me; but the woman was firſt in the tranſgreſſion, how can it be but there muſt needs follow a fearefull falling away? when men, or women, love the company, the diſcourſe, the writings of the groſſeſt Sectaries of all ſorts, and loath the truth? And for theſe 2. that are his conſtant Hearers, there is no miſchiefe would bee thought on with us, were it not for them; their excuſe, when they ſay, or doe, what they may ſuffer for, is, that they were drunke. One of them would have hired a Neighbour to fall out with me; hee offered him money at ſeverall times; but the honeſt man hated ſuch an horrible wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; and told mee how hee tempted him. They have ſworne both of them, even to the taking away of life; I ſay not, forſworn. Like <hi>Salamanders,</hi> they delight to live in the fire; if any Brangle bee with us, or about us, O brave! They are like thoſe fiſhes, that love trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters; like Flies; they ſit either on ſore places, or are padling in dung; and <hi>Baalzebub</hi> is the God of theſe Flies. They ſay, <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> left a Rule to all his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Phyſitians, which he commanded them to obſerve, on paine of his Curſe; it was this; That they ſhould Cure others with Medicines, Simple and Compound; themſelves, with Sack, and Claret: But theſe Men (if I
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:118118:42"/> may call them Men) uſe the ſame Phyſicke themſelves, that they preſcribe to others: yet if they do goe to Hel, as <hi>Roboald</hi> K. of <hi>Weſt-Fryſons,</hi> ſaid, they may find ſome of their friends, if the Divell dare let them come thither; there's the doubt, left they trouble him, as much as they doe us. I, and mine, are bound to bleſſe God, that the elder Brother could not tell how to be ſo wicked, as the yonger would have had him; for hee is <hi>plenus rimarum,</hi> full of holes, as a Riddle, and can hold nothing; any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or a cup of Ale, may ſet open the Stable doore, and let out the Aſſe within. And which is ſtrange, yet true, Lions and Beares are won with kindneſſes; but theſe men are worſe then Beaſts; Doe them a courteſie (and you dare not but doe it) then, who dare meddle with them? as if they could ſet the Divell, as they doe their Dogs, on any thing.</p>
            <p>They ſay, <hi>Amphions</hi> Muſick made the ſtones to dance, and drew them after him; ſavadge men they meant, ſure, that were before ſenceleſſe as ſtones: they tell us, that the <hi>Dolphins</hi> ſaved <hi>Arions</hi> life, becauſe he playd and ſung ſo ſweetly: the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> undertooke to cure the Melancholy; nay, the Mad mans fury by Muſicke. When the evill <hi>Spirit</hi> from God was upon <hi>Saul, David</hi> took a Harp, and playd with his hands; ſo <hi>Saul</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, and was well, and the evill Spirit departed <hi>from him,</hi> 1. Sam. 16. 23. I have often heard out of many a Miniſters mouth ſuch ſweet Melody, as paſt <hi>Arions</hi> and <hi>Amphions</hi> skill, beyond compare; put down the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> Pipes; it muſt bee ſhort of that ſweet Singers tongue, tis true; not of his Harp and Hand, though they warbled never ſo well; and yet the Divell doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from <hi>Saul,</hi> he is as ill as ever: <hi>Wee pipe but they will</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:118118:42"/> 
               <hi>not dance:</hi> I had rather undertake to charme a hungry Lions mouth, to winne a Tyger, or to meet a wild ſhee Beare, and make her tame, then to mollifie or make a change in theſe mens manners: never men tooke more paines to be vertuous, then they doe to bee vitious; no <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> can cure their ill Conditions.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe they doe that which (I truſt in God) the Devill by their meanes ſhall never bee able to doe; yet as <hi>Epaminondas</hi> ſaid of his two Daughters, the Battails of <hi>Mantinea,</hi> and <hi>Leuctra;</hi> ſo may I ſay too, <hi>this Daughter of mine is like to out-live their cruelties, and vindicate her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers credit againſt the Opinions, and the Practiſes of ſuch ſhameleſſe Sectaries: Having obtained helpe of God, I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to this day,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in ſuch a Caſe, Acts 26. 22. though they are and have beene very <hi>Jewes</hi> unto mee: and come what can come, it ſhall be welcome; if I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſecured from the troubles of men on Earth; yet I know nothing can hurt mee that comes from God in Heaven. Now let Mr. <hi>T.</hi> tell mee truly, if ſuch <hi>Phaetons,</hi> as ſet the world on fire, be fit Companions for Miniſters; if yet he be a Miniſter, which who beleeves? Birds of one feather will flie together; but I cannot hear that ever he uſed the Company of any Miniſter: nay, hath he not, doth he not <hi>abdicare ſe ab Officio,</hi> put off the Office (as they doe that renounce their Baptiſme) by joyning in the right hand of fellowſhip, and admitting equally men of any Trade or Occupation, to Preach, or Teach with him in publick, though they be no Miniſters? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Biſhops, and Presbyters are an abomination to him; and as for the People, they cannot make a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il dat, quod non habet;</hi> no Cauſe can give to the Effect, that which it hath not firſt in it ſelfe: and hee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:118118:43"/> ought not to take that Office to himſelfe; it is againſt Heb. 5. 4. Therefore I doe not deny, but I doubt hee is no Miniſter. Let him remember, that may be lawfull <hi>in Eccleſia conſtituenda,</hi> which is not lawfull <hi>in Eccleſia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituta;</hi> that may bee lawfull in the planting, or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a Church, which is unlawfull afterward.</p>
            <p>However it be, his practiſe is againſt the 23. <hi>Article;</hi> the words of that Article are theſe: <q rend="margQuotes">It is not lawfull for any man to take upon him the Office of publicke Preaching, or Miniſtring the Sacraments, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, before he be lawfully called, and ſent to execute the ſame.</q> And theſe we ought to judge law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called and ſent, which be choſen, and called to this work, by men, who have publick Authority given un-unto them in the Congregation, to call and ſend Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters into the Lords Vineyard. I doe not inſtance in this Article, otherwiſe then as it agrees with the practiſe of all Proteſtant Churches in Europe; and it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the word of God, by ſuch Arguments, as it is impoſſible to anſwer.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtles were all ſent by our Saviour; firſt he furniſhed them with gifts, Mat. 10. 1. and then hee gave them their Commiſſion: verſe 5. <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> John 20. 21. If the people choſe the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> yet the <hi>Apoſtles layd their hands upon their heads, &amp;c.</hi> before they <hi>ſent</hi> them <hi>forth,</hi> Acts 6. 6. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas ordained Elders in every Church,</hi> Acts 14. 23. <hi>Take heed to the Flocks,, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers,</hi> Acts 20. 28. <hi>And yet they were all made Miniſters by Men, that were thus made by the Holy Ghoſt; Timothy</hi> was made a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> by the <hi>impoſition of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> 1. Tim. 4. 14. and <hi>Timothy</hi> made others <hi>Miniſters</hi> by the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:118118:43"/> 
               <hi>impoſition</hi> of <hi>hands,</hi> 1. Tim. 5. 22. and ſo did <hi>Titus,</hi> Tit. 1. 5. <hi>No man taketh</hi> (that is, ought to take) <hi>this honour unto himſelfe, but he that is called of God, as Aaron,</hi> Heb. 5. 4. <hi>who had as an inward, ſo an outward Call:</hi> Nay, <hi>Chriſt himſelfe gloried not himſelfe to be an High Prieſt, he had a Call,</hi> Heb. 5. 5. Neither the <hi>Heavens</hi> could abide to <hi>ſee,</hi> nor the <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>beare</hi> the ſhameleſſe <hi>burthen of ſuch as came unſent:</hi> but the one melting conſumed with fire; and the other o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening ſwallowed them up alive, Numb. 16. 32. 35. To ſay, that all the people are holy alike, hand over head, it was the ſin of <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Company, Numb. 16. 3. Common waters cannot heale ſo well, as the waters of Jordan, that had the Promiſe. That Argument of theirs, Is not the Spirit of God as effectuall in others, as in them they call Miniſters? is much like that of <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian; are not <hi>Abana,</hi> and <hi>Pharphar,</hi> Rivers of Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, better then any River of Iſrael? 2. Reg. 5. 12. The power of the Keyes is not in the People; the Promiſe was to the Apoſtles, and the Miniſters, their Succeſſors; and yet ſome of the People may have a greater meaſure of the Spirit, then many of the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>Becauſe ſuch a Captain may bee as able as his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, may he therefore uſurp the Office of his Generall? Becauſe many private Soldiers may bee as able as their Captain, may they therefore uſurp the Office of their Captaine? Becauſe many Lawyers may bee as able as the Judges may they therefore take upon them to bee Judges? Becauſe many Gentlemen may bee as honeſt as a Juſtice of Peace may they therefore take upon them to be Juſtices of Peace? they allow it not among them that are the Miniſters of our Parliament; then it may not be allowed among us who are the more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:118118:44"/> Miniſters of our God. Any Butcher might have killed a Bullock in Sacrifice as well or better then the Prieſts; but yet a King durſt not bee ſo bold; there are other means for private men to imploy their Gifts; they may not in Preaching publickely the Word of God. Who dare doe any thing in the name of the Parliament without a Commiſſion? Friend, how cameſt thou in hither, wee may well ſay to ſuch as take upon them the Office of the Miniſtry, without a Call? By what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority doſt thou thus, and who gave thee this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? The brazen Cenſers, wherewith they that were burnt, had offered, were made Bread-plates for a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Altar, to bee a memoriall, that no ſtranger, who is not of the ſeed of <hi>Aaron,</hi> come neer to offer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe before the Lord, that he be not, as <hi>Korah,</hi> Numb. 16. 39. 40. All this I have ſayd, is nothing unto that which may be ſayd, both againſt the Opinions, and the Practiſes of the Brethren about us: and yet I have ſayd enough, had I wiſe men to deale withall; but bray my Adverſaries in a Mortar, and they will be the ſame. I know that God, that made the heart, can mollifie their ſtony hearts; Chriſt can open their eyes, as hee did the two Diſciples, that ſaw him not, though they ſat at meat with him, Luke 24. 30. 31. No more then <hi>Hagar,</hi> did the Well, that was ſo neere, till God opened her eyes alſo, Gen. 21 19. Even the ſame God, for Chriſts ſake, pity this poore, ſimple, ſeduced People. And ſo I draw to a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Now then conſider what I have ſayd, and the Lord give you underſtanding: and I beſeech Mr. <hi>T.</hi> by the Death and Paſſion of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that he ſeek no more to tear Chriſts ſeameleſſe Coat; wee are
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:118118:44"/> Brethren, travailling towards our heavenly Country; let us not fall out by the way: Preach the truth in love; ſend home wandring ſheep to their owne Folds; but infect them not; or ſo metamorphize them, that they turne Woolves, come home, and worry their owne Shepheards. The Office of an Evangeliſt is now ceas'd; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, buſie Biſhops, or buſie Presbyters, in other mens Pariſhes, are forbid, 1. Pet. 4. 15. He reckons ſuch among Murtherers, and Thieves: take heed to the Flocks, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers, Acts 20. 28. Where is any warrant to meddle with other mens Flocks? <hi>Paul</hi> thought it not good to take <hi>Marke,</hi> becauſe he went not, at firſt, with them to the Work, Acts 15. 38. He is too bold, that builds upon another mans Foundation.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant me to diſcharge my own Charge, for who is ſufficient? But let not Mr. <hi>T.</hi> meddle in every mans Charge; it may argue courage in him (ſo I call it) not diſcretion. I ſhut up all with the advice of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his Epheſians, Epheſ. 4. <hi rend="margQuotes">Since hee hath given ſome Apoſtles, ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Saints, for the worke of the Miniſtery, and for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt: bee not henceforth any more Children, toſſed to, and fro, and carryed about with every winde of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftines of thoſe that lye in wait to deceive; but ſpeaking the truth in love, grow up to him in all things, which is our Head, even Chriſt; from whom the whole Body fitly joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, according to the effectuall working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the Body, to the edifying of it ſelfe in love.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:118118:45"/>
            <p> And therefore if there be any conſolation in Chriſt; if any comfort of love; if any fellowſhip of the Spirit; if any bowels and mercies, fulfill my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, and of one Judgement; endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace: knowing that there is but one Body, one Spirit, one Hope of our Calling, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God, and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in us all. Behold, how good and pleaſant it is, for Brethren to dwell together in unity: it is like the precious ointment, that was powred upon <hi>Aarons</hi> beard; as the dew of Hermon; and as the dew that deſcended upon the mountains of Zion, Pſal. 133. If all the Graces of a Chriſtian ſhould make one Ring, Love would bee the Diamond; there the Lord promiſed his Bleſſing, and Life for evermore, where there is Love. Now the very GOD, who is Love, ſanctifie us throughout; and I pray God that our whole ſpirit, and ſoul, and body, may be preſerved blameleſſe unto the comming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the God of Peace and Love, 1. Theſſ. 5. 23. Unto the ſame God, that is able to keep you from falling, and to preſerve you faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joy; To the only wiſe God our Saviour be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Majeſty, Dominion, and Power, now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
